哦。
佢有手啊！
都算都算。
誒。
早晨。
啊！佢哋就啊，陳。
我唔中意唱那些。
噉佢哋嘅人。
人名哦，OK OK。
啱咧就夠人數，我哋開會咧。
噉啊！呢個上邊咧就五月二十九就會討論呢兩個問題。
啊！今日出席嘅嗰個會議嘅係有黃浩源先生，嚇財經事務局同埋副局個常任秘書長。
咁如果誒冇嘢嘅話咧，我哋就進入第四個咧，就係金融科技嘅發展。噉我哋請政府嘅官員介紹。
同埋咧，誒為就打擊與放債業務有關嘅不良手法而實施四大訓就應對付措施嘅新嘅發展啊！
嗰個以前就確確認咧，通過會議同埋誒紀要嘅記錄。噉啊，呢個啊，如果冇意見就誒，我哋去第二個item啦。就啲文件咧誒已經畀曬誒各位議員嘅啦啊，噉啊，大家都收到啦。
第三嘅議程咧，就下一次討論嘅日期同時間。噉我哋就定喺下一個誒議會嘅時間，就係定喺五月二十九號啊。如果冇問題嘅五月二十九號，噉啊個討論嘅事項咧就兩個，一個就係香港金融管理局嘅工作報告。
dition is happening in January.
另外一位係李樹培先生，香港金融管理局助理總裁。
誒數碼港嘅誒阿阿湛博士同埋金誒金管局阿李先生一間介紹一下佢哋誒相關做緊工作，或者我交咗畀阿Charles先，Charles。好啊。
規管上邊咧，三個嘅金融監管機構咧都設立咗金融科技專用嘅誒平台，加強同業界嘅溝通。另外咧，支付系統同埋儲值支付工具條例已經全面實施。
啊，夏多斯夏多希先生，投資推廣處。噉啊，另外一個黃其源先生，啊財經事務及副務局首席助理秘書長。啊，另外一位係岑家揚博士，香港數碼啊港管理有限公司工作。
同市民嘅總金啊，歡迎啊，政府嘅官員啊，同我哋介紹一下關於嗰個啊金融科技嘅發展。唔該誒，早晨，主席誒各位議員早晨誒，今日咧誒，我喺度就同大家介紹下誒誒，我哋舊年都有嚟呢個事務委員會度匯報。
關於喺金融科技發展方面，我哋做嘅工作誒，大家記得咧，特區政府喺二零一五年嘅四月咧，就成立咗由財經事務及副務局局長領導嘅金融科技督導小組。咁仲喺喺去年嘅月咧，我哋公佈咗嗰個報告嘅。
咁誒就提提出咗咧，喺五個範疇嘅建議咧，去推動香港金融科技嘅發展。噉就包括咧，就係推廣方面啦、支援措施方面啦、規管方面啦、資金咧同埋人才五方面嘅。咁政府參考咗嗰個小組嘅報告之後咧，喺過去一年咧聯。
同我哋各國嘅金融監管機構同埋相關嘅持份者咧，就就住呢五個範疇咧推出咗一係列唔同嘅措施。喺推廣方面咧，我哋喺投資推廣署下邊成立咗專責小組，就去致力吸引初創嘅企業、投資者同埋誒依個誒科研。
嘅機構咧落户喺香港嘅喺依個支援措施方面咧，數碼港誒等嘅機構咧就推出咗支援初創企業嘅措施，例如金融科技嘅專屬空間同埋相關嘅培訓計劃，就促進金融機構同埋初創企業嘅協作啦。
咧金管局同埋數碼港亦都推出咗努力編程加速器嘅計劃，金管局亦都推出咗措施咧，鼓勵應用依個尖端金融科技啦，例如依個誒網絡嘅防衞計劃同埋依個進行依個區誒區塊鏈嘅研究喺。
有助確保咧電子錢包安全穩健，就加強公眾使用呢一類嘅產品同埋服務嘅信心。金管局亦都推出咗呢個監管沙盒嘅措施咧，鼓勵業界創新喺推喺推廣各項嘅措施嘅時候咧，我哋會繼續秉持呢個。
科技中立嘅原則嘅喺資金方面，政府同誒政府嘅企業支援計劃，同埋數摩數碼港嘅誒投資創業基金，為呢個金融科技嘅創新項目提供咗呢個資助嘅渠道。而最後咧喺人才方面咧，我哋。
就着眼係培育新一代嘅金融科技人才，誒，例如金管局同埋應科院推出嘅金融科技人才培訓計劃，以及數碼港同大學合作嘅夥伴計劃。或者，主席，你容許我我請幾位，包括誒誒投資推廣署金融科技主管。
Good morning. In the limit of Invest Hong Kong in the promotion of fintech in Hong Kong, we are committed to promote Hong Kong as a fintech hub. So we've got different initiatives. Among them are the Fintech Week, which we organised for the first year last year, and we had over 2,500 attendees. This year, 2
謝謝。
住喺香港。
作為我們的同事，監管者。
咁去到二零一七年二月底，係呢個數字。
誒佔輪率咧已經超過七七十五個percent，而固定工作方工作站咧四十percent。
咁咧，同埋依個誒，所有嘅領袖咧，佢哋都可以瞭解到金融科技對佢哋嘅一個影響。
誒，對於呢個問題有冇意見啊？仲有啊，博士係OK，繼續啊！
2017， we're going to get also a second edition of the FinTech Week running. It will be hosted at the Hong Kong Convention Centre at the end of October. We also organise another event which is a grassroots event, the FinTech Finals, which second editions will come within part of the StartMeUp Festival. This
In our job of promotion and facilitations, we are on regular basis engaged with international media outside of Hong Kong, to name a few cities: London, Copenhagen, Shanghai, Shenzhen, Paris, New York and San Francisco, and we hold also different international media promotion events to make sure that.
Hong Kong value proposition updates are shared with international media and audiences. The team of fintech at Invest Hong Kong is spread over Hong Kong, London and San Francisco to get the closest we can from the different fintech ecosystem and be engaged with different companies we want to.
So far, we've been assisting more than 40 different overseas companies, helping them to find offices in Hong Kong, helping them with their working visa, as well as finding different business services. We do regular introductions to Cyberport for fintech companies who wants to to to join Hong Kong and start up in Hong.
誒大家好，大家早晨。誒，我關於數碼講響金融科技發展，我分得五部分去誒去大家去睇一睇嘅。第一部分咧就係金融科技培訓計劃、培育計劃。噉我哋咧響有一個計劃叫大學合作計劃啦。就五年內咧，我哋會去培訓三百個大學生咧去海學咧學呢個。
金融科技嘅，咁蘇花嚟講咧，誒過去兩年咧，我哋已經超過有一百零五個學生咧去過Stanford咧去學習呢個金融科技嘅。第二咧就係我哋個培育計劃，培育計劃即係我哋incubation program。噉我哋已經有五十四間金融科技嘅初創企業咧參與咗我哋呢方面嘅培育計劃。
第三個咧就係我哋去誒一啲初創企業咧，佢參加啲全世界比較出名啲嘅，我哋叫加速器啦。噉我哋有一個支援咧，就係有三十萬，佢哋可以申請咧去參加啲海外嘅加速器。咁呢個第一部分響培育方面嘅，第二部分咧就空間啦。噉我哋響金融科技初創企業裏邊咧，我提。
供一個專屬嘅工作空間，我哋叫Smart Space嘅FinTech。咁喺誒二零一六年十二月咧，我哋啟用咗啦。個面積咧大概係有四千三百平方米嘅。咁呢個咧就係完全係畀個金融初創企業咧去用嘅。咁誒，so far嚟講咧都一樣啦。我哋個辦公室嗰個
噉我哋亦都同一個世界比較出名嘅一啲加速器咧，金融科技嘅加速器咧，係係一齊合作嘅，就包括Essential啦，包括Supercharger啦。噉我哋一齊合作咧，係培養一啲誒金融初創企業咧，令到我哋再前去多幾步嘅。咁第三點咧，就係我哋。
關於依個誒增進依個金融企業嘅合作啦，咁響多方面，我哋同業界咧係不斷嘅合作啦。特別係一個金融嘅業界啦。咁譬如響二零一七年一月嘅時候，亞洲金融論壇嘅時候咧，我哋響裏邊舉辦咗個金融科技嘅研討會啦，可以令到誒亞太區嘅財長。
進展嘅啊，唔該曬。
好，仲有阿李生啦。
O.K.，仲有另外一位啊。
嘅研究一啲概念嘅認證啊，各方面等等。咁過幾個月已經有五間銀行同埋三間嘅初創企業公司咧，用呢個地方咧做一啲啊概念認證嘅測試嘅。
咁第二樣嘅例子咧，就係我哋響同呢個誒數碼港啦，同呢個Astra啦，即係應用科技研究院啦，香港科學園咧同金融管理局咧，響去年嘅十一月咧，我簽訂咗一個M O U，就金融嘅科技合作亮解備忘錄，可以增加我哋幾方面一齊嘅合作咧。
咁誒，亦都一個好緊要嘅就係我哋三月啱啱推出咗同呢個香港M A即係金融管理局咧，我哋推做一個叫Hexagon嘅一個嘅計劃，叫努力程式設計加速器嘅計劃。咁呢個咧係鼓勵咧香港嘅年輕人咧就初創企業咧去去解決一啲銀行裏邊嘅一啲問題嚇。有邊個？
啊！仲有仲有兩點，我係補充埋先，好快嚇。咁第四就係大家都好重視嘅區塊鏈咧。我哋發展區塊鏈咧，亦都做咗好多不同嘅方法研討會啦，同呢個Hong Kong M A合作啦，同埋咧響引入一個誒世界科技，譬如I B M嚟培訓我哋。最後一個咧就係資金問題啦。咁香港亦都好緊要咧，需要啲資金去支持我哋初創。
企業噉，我哋響誒去年嘅八月咧，我哋推出個兩億嘅誒投資創業基金咧，去支持咧我哋一啲初創企業再發展再下一步。咁so far嚟講咧，亦都有一百間嘅公司咧，已經係去問過依個誒依個投資嘅創業基金。咁希望咧就好快去將來咧可以announce到咧一啲。
議員啊，早晨，你哋好啊！咁金管局咧喺去年咧配合政府推廣呢個金融科技嘅啊，促進喺香港嘅發展咧，我哋金管局都去年三月就成立咗一個金融科技嘅促進辦公室。咁個其中嘅主要目的咧，就希望喺香港咧能夠啊，造成一個生態圈啦，比金融科技更加啊有效。
果嘅發展噉，我哋咧有誒短期、中期同埋長期嘅啊計劃嘅。噉我哋誒我簡簡單單去講一講呢中誒短中長期嘅計劃啦。嗱，第一樣嘢短期嘅咧，我哋咧就先建立一個平台。咁呢個平台咧就有誒畀金融啊科技嘅啊。
誒誒，應要可以發畀啲學生，而喺七月份咧，佢哋係可以進行呢個嘅實習嘅機會嘅。啊，今朝佢分享到呢度嚇。
兩個比較誒規模好大嘅經濟咧，係有一個距離，但係喺其他咧，實在香港今日唔係做得太差。多謝主席。
嘅問題啊，風險管理等等，我哋將會喺今年嘅下半年咧，我哋希望可以出到第二份嘅白皮書畀業界，可以多一啲嘅參考。而當中我哋希望喺應用方面咧，我哋喺按揭啊、貿易融資啊同埋啲啊身份認證嘅方面咧，希望試一試呢個科技可唔可以應用喺當中嘅。
者咧有一個平台去交流同埋一個合作嘅。咁過去呢誒一年嘅期間咧，我哋舉辦咗超過十場嘅誒活動嘅。咁當中亦都有超過二千五百個參與者嚟自世界唔同嘅地方啦、啊銀行啦、金融啊企業啦，甚至一啲初創嘅公司或者一啲監管機構咧，我哋一個平台。
畀佢互相嘅交流同埋合作，咁亦都同啊應科院啦、數碼港同埋啊香港嘅科技園，我哋都簽咗合作備忘，好一齊去推廣呢個金融科技。咁亦都喺跨境嘅方面咧，我哋去年咧都同英國嘅啊金融行為監管局或者我哋叫F.C.A.啦，就簽證一個合作啊協議嘅，我哋一齊。
去推廣嗰啲跨境嘅啊金融科技嘅創新嘅。咁喺啊，另外第二個短期嘅措施咧，我哋喺好短時間，我哋成立咗一個有效嘅監管嘅界面。咁呢個界面，我哋希望咧可以幫助誒一啲初創企業啊，或者一啲銀行咧，當佢推行一啲啊金融創新嗰時咧，更加有效去做嘅嗱噉。
咁第一個措施，誒喺呢個界面裏邊咧，我哋成立咗個金融科技嘅監管嘅沙盒，或者我哋俗稱嘅sandbox。咁喺呢個短短嘅大約五六個月嘅時間咧，已經有十四個項目咧，經過呢個沙盒咧，完成咗一個概念嘅認證啊，或者測試，甚至有啲已經推出喺市場咧，畀市民嚟應用嘅。咁當中。
中有包括啲生物認證啊，或者應用啊程式嘅界面啊、區塊鏈等等噉樣嘅。咁亦都喺誒，據去年咧，我哋誒通過咗呢個支付系統及儲值支付工具嘅條例之後咧，我哋都加緊去去批出呢個牌照咧，已經有十三間嘅支儲值支付工具咧喺香港可以運作。
而提供畀市民更多唔同嘅支付嘅啊啊選擇嘅。咁另一樣嘢，我哋亦都同呢個應科院合作咧，啊，成立咗一個金融科技嘅創新中心。而呢個係一個地方咧，係畀一啲創想企業同銀行咧一齊有一個地方有資源同埋有啲設施咧，畀佢去做一啲科研。
嗱咁喺第三方面啦，就呢啲比較中期嘅啦。噉我哋咧就做一啲誒同業界做一啲研究啦，同埋點樣應用一啲最新嘅金融科技。噉就誒第一樣嘢，我哋去年十月已經推出一個網絡防衞嘅計劃。咁呢度網絡防衞計劃咧就包括三樣嘢嘅，就係畀銀行咧有一個網絡防衞嘅評估嘅框架，點樣？
去認定佢哋嘅水平係達到咩嘅標準？第二樣嘢咧，亦都建立咗一個網絡風險資訊共享嘅平台，能夠銀行之間咧將一啲保安資訊咧可以互相去交流、互相去去去分享噉樣。咁亦都有一個專業嘅培訓計劃等等喺呢個網絡安全。咁另外一樣嘢咧，就我哋覺得都要需要多一啲時間深。
多多一啲噉嘅研究咧，就係所謂俗稱嘅blockchain或者區塊鏈。咁去年誒去年嘅十一月咧，我哋已經發出咗第一份嘅白皮書，對呢個區塊鏈嘅認識，我哋希望加深畀業界多一點嘅認識。但係我哋覺得咧，仲有啲嘢我哋更加需要再深入嘅研究，包括佢嘅法律嗰方面嘅問題啊、監管。
咁第三樣嘢咧，就其實喺過去兩個星期，我哋金管局宣佈咧，就係關於央行啊發行呢個嘅啊啲啊數碼貨幣。嗱，咁呢個係好初期嘅階段嘅。咁而家喺世界各地咧，好多中央銀行已經進入一一啲嘅初步嘅研究，而我哋金管局亦都進行呢個初步嘅研究，亦都未有定論嘅。我哋
睇睇，如果央行發行呢個數碼貨幣嘅話，個風險對貨幣嘅政策、金融穩定嘅影響，甚至保安各方面，其實係咪誒做得夠嘅咧？喺呢方面，噉我哋要做一啲研究，去多多多一點嘅認知，然後決定下一步嘅計劃。嗱，咁喺比較長遠嘅啦，長遠嘅措施咧。
我哋第四項咧，我哋進一步優化我哋金融基建啦。噉我哋都啊啊宣佈咗咧，就係會啊建立一個快速支付嘅系統。呢個係一個七成二十四嘅小額嘅支付系統，能夠令到啊市民啊或者一啲商户啊一啲企業咧，可以係即時做一啲支付同。
同埋即時嘅交收嘅即時嘅結算嘅，噉我哋希望呢個系統可以喺明年嘅年底咧推出啊去市場嘅。咁第五行啦，呢個就更加唔係一招一夕啦，要一個比較長遠嘅啊投資同埋計劃裏邊。噉我哋喺人才培訓啦，咁呢樣嘢咧，我哋覺得啊冇一個地方係足夠嘅，所以我哋香港更加需要。
要係一啲長遠嘅計劃噉，我哋啊金管局咧就同埋應科院就同十二間銀行，亦都啊有十間嘅大專院校一齊合作咧，推出一個金融科技人才嘅培訓計劃。咁今年係第一年我哋推出嘅，我哋希望係有一百個以上嘅學生咧，能夠有六個月至一年嘅實習時間去到銀。
銀行裏邊咧係做一啲真真正正嘅金融創新嘅項目，喺參與嘅當中去學習。咁誒，而家我哋收收到超過三千份嘅申請啦，裏邊多誒包括有四百多個學生。咁而家進行緊面試嘅，我哋希望喺啊五月內咧就可以啊將呢個誒。
主席，最後或者誒提一提喺我哋提交畀委員會嘅文件裏邊咧，都有兩個表嘅，就係一個咧就係睇一誒我哋最近嘅調查，睇下究竟香港整體嗰個初創金融誒科技企業嗰個數目，咁依個都係一個即係顯示啦，我哋做咗。
一啲措施，個生態係一路不斷噉係誒誒，即係誒優化緊。咁另外咧，亦都誒好多時我哋見到報章都有有提及啦。究竟即係嗰個誒籌集資金方面做成點咧？噉我哋亦都喺文件度咧，畀咗一個。
表咧係作為一個參考嘅啫。咁依個咧亦都係一間出邊嘅誒公司做嘅一個誒二零一四至零一六年度亞太區金融科技風險投資嘅一啲數據嚟嘅。咁依個亦都可以顯示咧，即係我哋雖然比起中國同埋印度嚟講，
哦。
周浩鼎。啊，周浩鼎。
佢畀佢測試一啲新嘅科技。
上一次我哋誒呢邊嘅議員同事都提出過呢個問題嘅，噉我想睇下呢方面咧，政府又有咩對策去釋除大家嘅疑慮咧？唔該，主席。
所以依個誒，我哋會不時檢討我哋嗰個規管上嘅要求，睇下邊啲嘢我哋可以令到嗰個業界佢哋碰到嘅問題，我哋有一個好啲嘅方法去解決。或者我請請阿樹培講講誒，即係我哋點樣去鼓勵誒依一啲同埋喺網絡安全方面。
好啊！多謝誒，政府嘅介紹。而家誒，我哋有六位嘅議員想發言。咁仲有冇？嗱，第一位係梁誒陳振英議員、陳建波、郭明鏗、梁繼章、木乃光誒姚創賢，仲有冇？
啊！大致上，每個人咧，連問連答咧四分鐘啊。唔該，第一位係陳振英議員。誒，多謝主席喺誒文件同埋投影片嘅資料顯示咧，就誒本港個金融科技業喺過去十二個月進展都係顯著嘅，噉嘅情況都令人有啲鼓舞啦。咁但係我哋好緊要嘅睇下今。
金融機構嘅一啲睇法啦。啱最近期咧，羅冰涵永道咧做咗第二期嘅全球金融科技調查嘅結果，就反映咗本港金融機構就金融科技發展嘅取態嘅噉就有三方面。第一，憂慮會增加監管方面嘅不確定性咧，就佔六十percent，噉就高過全。
全球嘅五啊四個percent，第二咧就認為咧會對資訊保安同埋私隱嘅風險咧就會達到七十二percent，又明顯高於全球嘅四十八個percent。第三咧就係對金融科技嘅投入咧佔收入嘅比例咧，平均就係得十四個percent，就略略低於。
全球嘅十五點四個percent咁呢個調查結果咧，就反映咗誒本港受訪啲金融機構咧對金融科技發展咧就有個比較審慎嘅態度啦。噉我問題有兩個嘅，第一個咧就係誒佢哋講嘅第一點誒擔心、憂慮監管方面嘅不確定性啦。咁喺我哋立法會文件咧。
誒C.B.一六一七零四號文件嘅第十段都講過咧，政府對誒金融科技嘅規管架構咧係採取咧就話，因為國際社會冇一個通用嘅模式，所以就採用一個叫科技中立嘅原則。咁誒，因為咁咧，可能會更加就係業界對嗰個不確定性咧就會有一個。
個傳疑喺度咁誒，政府喺呢方面會有咩解決或者睇法咧？呢個係第一方面嘅。第二個方面就係第二點㗎啦，講到話對資訊保安同埋私隱嘅風險咧，誒咁高個憂慮係七十percent同四十八個percent誒，咁一定係擔心呢樣嘢啦。噉我記得誒睇翻文件咧，誒。
誒，政府邊個回應？誒，主席或者我講幾個，我請阿阿阿雪培講講。即係當然喺規管上邊咧，實實質上咧，而家政府係誒，我哋做咗幾個誒監管機構同埋業界嘅溝通平台。咁依個咧，正正因為金融服務咧，無論你講緊銀。
銀行、現鈔或者係誒證券都好咧，係牽涉一個即係投資者或者係用家嗰個保護嘅問題，所以一定要有個平衡。所謂我哋採取一個中立咧，我哋就話唔會特別優待，但係唔代表我哋嘅嘢係貼民一塊。好似我哋剛才提到誒支付系統，我哋。
通過經過立法會成立咗新嘅法例之後咧，有咗新嘅規定咧，市場係比較知道嗰個規管要求係咩，咁可能咧大家都見到過去十二個月咧喺依方面咧嘅支付系統依啲新嘅誒服務、新嘅誒服務提供者咧係多咗好多嘅，噉。
好誒，唔該，主席嗱。咁其實咧，誒，我哋監管機構咧，同以往已經嘅做法係幾大嘅分別嘅。今日我哋係走出去嘅，我哋去揾佢哋一齊去傾，亦都嘗試去了解佢哋嘅困難。咁好似譬如我哋個沙盒呢樣嘢啦，嚇噉我哋容許佢有一啲嘅環境裏邊咧，同埋業界同埋一啲初創。
嗱，咁其實而家我哋誒三個監管機構咧，都有一個聯絡點畀佢哋嘅。若果佢哋有問題咧，可以直接揾我哋。嗱，咁而監管局咧亦都誒，我哋搞好多嘅活動。而家差唔多每個月，我哋都有一啲活動去搞嘅。咁而係呢啲咧就係同有關嘅持份者佢哋參與參與裏邊，佢可以問一啲問題。啊，即係好簡簡單誒呢個。
講講即係喺誒監管方面嗰個問題。
我哋係加強下呢方面，令到嗰個資訊保安可以去到一個更高嘅水平。
一啲金融嘅創新啊，一啲科技創新咧，係要比較一個快嘅空間同埋彈性嘅空間畀佢哋去做嘅。如果用翻以前嘅模式咧，可能就唔係咁適合。
係更加有效去幫助到佢發展啲新嘅概念。我最後問多一條啦，啊！如果我哋面對深圳咁強勁啊，無論喺人才啊或者個條件都咁好，香港點同呢個深圳競爭？
啊，風險個方面啦，即係呢個資訊科技風險裏邊咧，嗱，我哋就啱啱去年十月推出咗呢個網絡安全嘅計劃，咁亦都要所有香港銀行咧都要做呢個評估，同埋咧我哋有啲平台咧畀佢分享啲資訊，一啲才誒人才培訓各方面，所以呢啲咧我哋係睇重呢樣嘢嘅緊要嘅。Cybersecurity相關。
誒，第二位係誒陳建波議員。多謝主席。誒，文件第十段咧有講到係關於金融科技嘅規管啊。咁入邊講到咧就話，政府拆釋金融科技公司所提供不少服務咧，可在現行法律架構下運作。而家國際上咧亦都冇一個即係通用嘅模式噉樣。咁但
但係我哋好多時同佢哋傾咧，好多時佢都係講話嗰個誒金融嘅規管咧，其實追唔上時代嘅。噉我想問一問政府咧，係咪即係覺得其實都唔係太多改變就已經處理到咧？咁即係譬如好簡單，你嗰啲監管銀行咧，監管實體銀行㗎嘛。咁如果喺一個網上銀行，你又點咧？你可唔可以講講政府係咪已經覺得好？
滿意而家呢個制度，覺得係唔需要再即係大嘅規模嘅改變咧。第二樣咧就係嗰個創新科技咧，我相信包括金融科技都係我哋香港呢下打後幾年重點嘅發展項目啦。咁其實呢樣做得好咧，係亦都係對呢個大學生嘅好好出路嘅嚇。咁但係即係都要嗰個大學個。
學生嘅修讀嘅科目係配合先得㗎。噉我想問一問政府喺呢方面點樣可以做到呢樣嘢咧？即係大學生有好出路，你又有足夠人才係嘛？咁然後去去去配合呢個科技發展，但係好明顯而家咧就好多科目都唔係好啱嘅，即係香港嗰個嗰個喺大學嗰個課程方面咧並唔能夠配合而家。
科技發展噉，我想問一問政府呢呢方面又點樣處理咧？嚇兩個問題。啊，辯主張誒主席，我答特議員嘅問題誒。喺培訓方面，即係我哋喺誒頭先剛才介紹都有講咧，我哋喺誒誒去優化香港嗰個金融科技整個大環境，其中我哋。
睇得到嘅要做嘅就係人才嘅培訓噉，所以咧即係除咗頭先誒誒數碼港，亦都有誒金誒依個金管局，亦都有做一啲誒人才培訓計劃，就係針對我哋嘅學生誒。我哋係提交畀誒誒委員會嘅文件第十段咧都有講誒，因為。
政府開始推廣呢個金融科技咧。而家我哋見到咧，誒香港中文大學同埋理工大學咧，已經有一啲係即係誒誒學位嘅課程係針對金融科技嘅。而我哋見到市場上邊咧，亦都有好多嘅專上學院咧，開始係發展一啲嘅課程，即係唔係。
係啊！秘書長喎，邊位？
我哋嘅希望就係嚟同我哋傾。
我哋嗰個誒彈性就係點咧？我哋唔會寫好多好多條文，睇完都唔明噉樣。我哋
佢想真係做生意做大嘅話咧，噉我哋有個申請牌照嘅渠道畀佢。而沙盒最終最終嘅目的係嘗試一啲概念，銀行去試都係試啲小規模，可能係一百幾十個客人或者佢嘅員工去試一啲真實嘅嘗試，然後去去推出嚟嘅。
主席啊，我諗唔係競金競爭咁簡單，我哋應該係多啲諗多啲方法咧，係同佢哋合作。依個依個係我哋應該走嘅路，因為人才始終係香港係有，但係我哋應該都同時利用國內嘅人才去幫我哋嘅企業。
新加坡、新加坡多好多配套？誒，佢誒細嘅一兩個人嘅一個金融科技嘅誒初創公司，佢哋都有好多配套係吸引佢哋。咁所以我唔喺香港做啦。噉你對依方面嘅嘅嘅嘢有啲咩回應咧？嚇？
係一個成年嘅係畀可能係一啲誒出咗嚟做嘢或者係想自己提升自己嘅誒一啲嘅誒專上課程咧，亦都係係集中喺金融科技嘅。噉我哋希望依一啲咧能夠提供機會畀我哋嘅年青人咧，可以向依一方面去諗下佢嘅發展。或者我請阿雪培。
嗱，頭先誒講過網絡誒網上銀行嗰個服務啦。其實網上銀行，我諗已經喺十幾接近二十年前開始慢慢慢慢推出嘅。咁其實監管哥喺十多年前已經有一個監管嘅嘅架構啊模式出咗嚟㗎啦。咁一路都係噉樣監管落去啊。而家我哋發覺嗰個最新嗰個走法咧，就係咧好多時。
呢個亦都其中個主要嘅原因咧，我哋推出沙盒，因為沙盒畀銀行同埋初創企業當中去嘗試啲新嘅概念嗰陣時候咧，我哋唔會成套監管規則擺落去嘅。我哋可以同佢逐個去傾，然後放鬆一啲地方，等佢可以更快嗱。而家我哋有十四個誒個案已經過咗嘅咧，我睇見咧就係佢短短可能幾個星期。
已經做完一啲概念性嘅測試，而佢發覺可行嘅話咧，佢就全面嘅發展啦。咁呢個就係我哋所畀到嘅彈性，而發覺咧係非常有效嘅嗱。而家仲有好幾間銀行，我哋喺度傾咧，繼續用呢個沙盒去發展啲新嘅理念同埋啲新嘅嘅技術嘅嚇。咁呢個我哋覺得係噉樣嘅方法。
好嘅，下一位啊，郭榮鏗議員，多謝主席。主席，我都係想問關於嗰個初創企業咧，同埋沙盒之間嗰個嘅關係。咁有好多嗰啲誒金融誒誒發展嗰啲誒初創企業咧，FinTech嗰啲咧，就同我講佢話沙盒咧，佢哋用唔到，因
因為咧沙盒咧都係畀一啲比較大嘅銀行同埋誒保險公司先可以用呢一個沙盒誒。佢哋呢啲太細啦，咁誒金管局又唔睺佢哋，即係香港又唔係好理佢哋。唔係真嘅，你唔好笑啊！咁咧好多就同我講話，我唔喺香港做啦。香港根本上冇噉嘅環境，我走去星。
係唔該，主席係啊，李生係係唔該，主席嚇嗱。我諗誒，可能對沙盒香港個誒申請或者用途咧有少混淆嘅。O.K.，我我解釋少少嚇嗱。我哋嘅沙盒咧係畀銀行同埋佢同一啲初創嘅合作嘅夥伴咧一齊用嘅，一齊試一啲新嘅概念。
嗱，如果純粹一個初創企業咧，一間誒技術嘅公初創企業公司咧，因為佢唔受我哋監管嘅，其實佢做唔需要去沙盒，佢可以自己去做喺個實驗室去做一啲譬如生物認證啊，誒一啲區塊鏈啊，佢如果覺得佢想嘗試啲新嘅概念措施咧，佢係唔需要畀人管嘅，佢可以去做嘅嚇。嗱，噉。
嗱，如果銀行同初創企業一齊合作，就嚟我哋傾。噉我哋可以放鬆啲咩畀佢喺短時間係三去嘗試。嗱，有啲初創企業咧，我我都面對過嘅。佢哋因為唔係太明白香港嘅監管架構咧，譬如啲做支付嘅，佢走嚟揾我哋傾，我想試一啲新嘅儲值支付嘅方法，但係誒，可唔可以用三？我話你唔需。
嗱呢個巴士停喺。
好，係一位啊，梁繼昌議員。
P.W.C.嗰個誒報告咧，尤其是喺香港。
講話到畀我聽，實質上對於我哋嘅消費模式，我哋嘅日常生活，呢個fast payment system會有啲乜嘢嘅改變？我係想知道嘅嚇，唔該。
啊！競爭啊、失業啊呢啲噉嘅狀況，其實唔應該係噉樣樣，但係我睇唔到政府喺呢一個方面咧，係做到任何啲工作去成為兩者之間嘅connection，因為點解咧？
誒花旗銀行開始有啲噉嘅改變咧，其實我哋睇到嚟緊第二個就恒生銀行咧都會做嘅，咁所以我哋一路落去咧，希望係解決個生態鏈嗰個大家個合作。咁呢個係啊，我希望補充嘅，唔該。係誒李生。
喺數碼港咧，佢哋有唔同嘅計劃，係去令到初創企業咧係唔會覺得，或者銀行誒，我哋現有嘅金融誒企業咧係唔會覺得佢哋同啲初創企業咧係打對台。好，我而家請阿李雪培講講關於誒嗰個FastPay。
需要嘅嗱，我哋嗰個規管就有個exemption嘅。有如果佢個額係低過某程度，佢唔需要同我哋傾。幾多啊？而家個額係？誒，一百萬。一百萬嚇嗱。咁當然佢話，如果佢多過呢個嘅話，佢點樣咧？噉佢佢容易多過一百萬嘅啫。即係譬如我識一個初創企業，佢係幫誒，譬如幫一。
啲費用去做嗰個轉，即係誒轉嗰個錢嘅。咁誒，佢可能佢嗰個額係講緊好少，可能講兩千蚊每一個誒transaction，每一次交易兩千蚊。咁但係佢都超過一百萬，超過一百萬咧，佢又要被規管。咁但係問題係咧，你嗰啲頭先講嗰啲咩沙沙沙盒嗰啲咧？
啊！喂，佢哋嗰啲銀行唔蘇佢㗎嘛？銀行銀行咁大，佢喎梗係揾啲有規模嘅誒初創誒揾啲有規模嘅FinTech公司同佢夾啦。佢嗰啲就係跌咗喺中間啦。佢又唔係大到銀行會睺佢，保險公司唔睺佢，但係咧佢又唔係細到咧少一百萬喎。咁嗰啲嘅你點幫？
所以其實我哋點解要創呢個辦公室嘅好處就係我哋有一個誒contact嘅point畀佢哋，佢哋走嚟揾我哋傾，我哋解釋畀佢聽。今日我哋走出去嘅，我哋同佢哋傾，因為佢唔明白。嗱，頭先講話兩千蚊、三千蚊，佢加埋嗰個總共嘅誒成交可能好多，但係我哋唔係計嗰個數，係嗰個錢儲落個户口嗰度一。
一百萬。如果佢做嘅交易咧，甚至係可能佢轉嚟轉去係幾千萬咁咧，都冇問題嘅。最緊要佢收咗個客儲落去嗰個錢咧，擺攏喺度嗰個錢唔好多過一百萬。OK，因為佢係嘗試嘛。我哋沙盒嗰個原則就係佢試個概念先。如果覺得成功嘅話，
多謝主席。嗯，其實我想講翻一個比較誒基本嘅誒金融科技發展嘅問題。而家聽來聽去咧，似乎就係嗯一啲嘅初創企業同傳統金融機構之間咧係有個gap嘅。因為我頭先即係我都call翻啊陳振英議員，頭先call。
我諗傳統金融機構financial institution咧，係而家嗰個心態，可能係視呢一啲嘅金融科技或者金融科技嘅創投企業咧，係一個對手。佢哋會displace咗傳統金融產業嘅一啲服務，甚至令到某啲傳統金融機構面臨啊倒閉。
喺長遠嚟講，如果一啲大嘅傳統金融機構，比如啊J.P. Morgan啊、 Goldman，喂，我想收購呢幾間FinTech公司，畀幾廿億出嚟，根本個分定咧，我唔覺得係一個問題。問題我哋點樣去改動呢啲傳統金融機構嗰個價值觀同埋意？
型態去擁抱金融科技嘅發展，呢個係未來十年同埋二十年嘅問題。我諗政府有冇一啲嘅誒睇法咧？對呢方面同埋做會做啲乜嘢嘢咧？啊，另外咧第二個問題咧，主席，我想問一問嗰個fast payment system，你就講咗一句嘢喺嗰個投射影片嗰度誒，我想局。
做到呢樣嘢咧，但係嗱，而家我哋講講下已經三個局嘅啦，依度坐咗喺度，咁點樣先至可以做到呢樣嘢咧？唔該，主席。
噉我哋就喺呢六劃線啦。噉啊，而家仲有一個木乃江要創業，周浩鼎啊，葉劉淑儀啊，喺六劃線。如果等陣再入嚟嘅，我哋又唔夠時間啊。
好，仲有冇人要發言嘅？因為時間關係啊，即係我哋要劃線，我哋要劃線嚇。仲有冇後邊入嚟嘅？啊，葉體有份。好，噉。
嗱，我哋即係建個平台，可以做到呢樣嘢，而喺喺個平台上邊，佢提供嘅服務咧，我哋就畀佢百花齊放去做。噉我哋知道，譬如話佢哋可能會係用電郵啊，誒，甚至係手提電話號碼，甚至一啲其他咧，可以認證到嗰個就係我要支付畀嗰間公司或者嗰個人啊。
主席，我或者我誒請請阿阿Donald Trump講講，因為我哋實其中我哋誒想優化香港嗰個誒金融科技整個生態咧，其中一個目的咧係希望多啲嘅現有金融機構係同初創企業去合作嘅，咁所以咧。
多謝楊建陽問題。誒，冇錯㗎，嗰個睇法係嘅。好緊要就係個成個生態鏈裏邊咧，誒，金融機構，譬如銀行咧，點樣可以佢個心態上邊有改變？咁所以點解我哋同誒呢個金管局咧合合作搞一個努力程式設計加速器嘅計劃咧？其實一個開始嚟嘅。咁個來源係點咧？其實。
實就係花旗銀行CityBank噉，佢都好open咧。希望可以睇多啲即係初創企業噉。啊，既然花花旗銀行需要嘅話咧，其實其他銀行都可能有咁需要，所以我哋就同金管局商量咧，不如我哋整體性去合作，即係將咧我哋嘅大嘅銀行咧可以參與，然後咧我哋。
數碼港有好多年青人同埋初創企業啦，亦都參與。個做法係點咧？佢哋出一個問題，喂，可能係點樣解決一個payment嘅問題，解決一個誒支付嘅問題？誒咁啲年青人點樣去幫手，可以有創意去解決咧？通過呢啲比賽又好，呢參與又好咧，令到兩邊都有改變嘅。
即係銀行咧，佢哋嘅心態咧就係可能啲高層都好想有創新，但係個問題咧就係中層咧，佢未必感受到嗰個好處，反而睇到咧係一個威脅。咁通過呢啲噉嘅實驗咧，或者一啲噉嘅合作咧，可以令到佢哋公司咧唔係淨係創新嗰邊得益，係文化方面咧係有改變嘅。咁所以見到。
我哋希望係即時嘅，即時嘅誒傳送同埋即時兩邊嘅交收都會做埋嘅。嗱，噉佢個佢個主要分別咧，我哋希望將來咧，甚至咧，雙方係唔需要知道大家銀行户口號碼，而做一啲支付，譬如可以用佢嘅手提電話號碼啦，甚至可能係佢嘅電郵地。
止啦，甚至有其他嘅嘢嗱。咁呢個咧，我哋建嘅係嗰個平台。咁上邊嘅服務咧，就銀行同埋一啲支付、儲值支付工具咧。佢諗佢嗰個創新嘅理念啦，佢點樣去做呢個支付更加創新，更加令到客人咧覺得方便，更加令到誒佢可以甚至啲商户做多啲生意。
啊！呢個莫禮光唔該，係主席。誒，首先係贊下先。噉我諗咧，即係唔係成日都彈嘅金金融科技同埋，即係喺創新科技方面咧，算係做得比較好同埋主動㗎啦。我都想其他即係政府部門都學佢哋噉樣樣就好啦。咁誒，但係咧嗱，我諗頭先有啲議員都提過一啲嘅，我諗想提。
睇翻一啲根本性一啲嘅問題啦，根本性一啲嘅問題咧，其實誒監管嗰個不確定性，頭先都好幾位議員都提到啦，係重要嘅。噉我諗咧嗱，而家喺誒金管局今日上咗嚟啦，你哋一係列好多嘅建議、好多措施咧，其實我覺得個方向都係好啱，啲小問題可以慢慢解決。咁但係咧就即係。
今日反而邊個唔喺度嘅？證監會唔喺度，保監會唔喺度，即係你有一個叫做專用平台，咁唔可以有個專用平台咧，就好似佢哋就可以誒唔使翻學㗎嘛？係咪？佢哋都要交功課㗎嘛？嗱，最大嘅問題就係咧，我哋喺香港而家講，我哋唔可以金融科技，淨係講銀行㗎嘛？銀行做到嗰啲。
聯係匯率係仍然同一個系統。
B處長唔該。啊啊，好啊，陳生。
主席好快做做三，我諗要留相關嘅監管誒誒機構決定。但係我我哋我會我會轉達議員嘅意見畀其他兩個監管機構去考慮。
事咧係多啲依一方面嘅直接溝通。主席一句嘅要求同埋希望，即係政府去做啫，就係誒可唔可以叫證監會等等其他監管者都要做佢哋嘅沙盒，同埋有一個時間表去諮詢相關佢哋應該要改嘅法例。
以致到咧就係你哋而家評估去將來嗰個流速會同實體貨幣會，我估會快咗啦嚇，會快咗幾多，從而對於香港嘅通貨膨脹會構成一個誒乜嘢嘅預測壓力？呢啲唔知可唔可以簡單回應？
噉我哋金管局都做緊嘢啦，但係證監嗰邊又點咧？好多嘅金融科技嘅範疇，包括你話譬如點對點嘅借貸啊，譬如誒呢個資本嘅眾籌啊，等等呢啲地方咧，其實都係需要即係睇一啲法例上邊係咪要清晰化㗎嘛。咁嗰邊有冇一啲時間表啊？有冇一啲嘅計劃去做諮詢啊？
啊！等等咧，咁誒，你講嗰個沙盒沙盒之中，而家都係金管局下邊一個措施。咁頭先講到都要有銀行參與嘅，咁唔係銀行嗰啲，噉佢又唔使做咯。咁所以咧，我希望下一次即係都要叫埋其他嘅一啲監管者上嚟啦。即係唔係成日都要同新加坡比較，但係新加坡嗰度咧，佢哋嗰個金管局咧。
我嘅睇到咧，就係話，除咗銀行咧、保險啦，佢話capital market intermediaries啦、誒stock exchange啦、誒同埋嗰個誒financial advisers咧，全全部都喺佢個範圍入邊嘅。噉佢可能係比較歸一啲啦。如果我哋唔係咁歸一嘅話，嗰個監管架構唔可以即時改嘅。咁政府開
可以做啲咩令到，譬如證監會等等係可以比較積極咧。咁另外咧就係即係好多議員都提到，我哋點同其他人競爭啦，譬如深圳啊等等。咁其實我真係發覺一點就係經常都同官員有分享嘅，就係話咧誒，其實而家傳統嘅金融中心已經唔係話即係發展金融科技就淨係。
佢哋先有優勢㗎啦，好多新興嘅，包括即係深圳之外，甚至乎你話三藩市啦、誒呢個直谷啦、誒澳洲啦等等，其實都開始做得好快嘅。咁有啲好多業者都同我講，其實我哋香港係可以利用翻我哋嘅優勢走出去嘅國際市場，特別係因為我哋瞭解中國嗰個金融科。
科技嗰個發展嘅一啲動向同埋一做法噉，而家我見咧，新加坡好深圳咧，全部都已經喺直谷嗰度咧，就係設立佢哋嘅辦事處，專係幫佢哋嘅創新嘅公司，包括金融科技打入去直谷嘅。因為嗰度咧，其實而家咧，直谷反而變咗一個世界嘅金融。
科技科技嗰方面嘅一個中心，噉我哋點樣去同佢合作咧？嗱，我都同Cyberport去過好多次，即係去過一次啦。你哋去過好多次啦，即係即係植谷啊嗰啲團，唔係去一次半次啊，係直情有個辦公室喺度日日去做嘢啊。咁香港可唔可以透過譬如Invest Hong Kong或者係誒即係其他嘅部門可以？
主席兩方面咧，誒雖然今日誒有金管局嘅同事喺度，誒依個S.F.C同埋依個保監嘅同事唔喺度，但係唔代表佢哋冇冇做佢哋要做嘅嘢。嗱喺喺誒即係證券方面，當然除咗頭先議員提嘅誒關於眾籌嗰嗰個話題之外咧。
當然，我哋見到咧，而家譬如robot advisor依啲嘅用緊fin tech technology喺香港誒依個證券市場咧，實在係發生緊嘅，係係已經出現咗㗎啦。咁而喺誒誒依個現鈔方面咧，我哋同誒Federation of Hong Kong Industry亦都一路有。
傾緊，我哋見到咧，現收公司而家採用FinTech去提供佢哋唔同嘅保險產品，個個個案咧亦都越嚟越高。咁至於頭先議員講緊話，誒我哋可唔可以即係向外多啲聯絡？失咗而家透過誒Sideport，透過誒投資推廣。
處咧，投資推進處頭先有介紹，我哋喺San Francisco而家係有一個small team，雖然係係因因為資源嘅問題，咁Singapore亦都係每年咧有同呢個誒有有舉行舉辦誒帶我哋一啲學生咧係去誒呢個Stanford University去做一。
好，阿周浩鼎演員咧。
所謂儲值支付工具嘅公司咧，可以參與喺我哋呢個fast payment嘅平台裏邊去發展嘅。啊，我哋希望係一個。
個方面我哋睇重少少啦，然後之後發覺如果技術真係未知之數嚇，如果譬如技術係某程度可能性嘅話咧，我哋叫擴大嘅研究嘅，而呢樣嘢唔係講緊一年半年嘅嘅研究，係一個比較長時間嘅嚇。唔該。
公司諗多啲新嘅系統咧，就不能夠再可能誒符合到嘅，會唔會有噉嘅情況？定還是係百花齊放，都歡迎佢哋有新嘅系統都可以入到嚟用到就得㗎啦。咁即係我就主要係呢樣嘢啦。誒第三咧，我亦都想問一問咧，就係。
啲bootcamp training嘅咁呢啲，我哋希望係開頭我哋做咁未來，我哋希望咧係同我哋好多唔同嘅counterparts咧，好似頭先誒金管局有講咧，同英國嘅監管機構而家有聯繫啦。我哋亦都希望咧可以將來同其他係有意發展金融科技嘅地方，包括內地嘅城。
好，要創院議員。主席，誒，我想係誒就住數碼貨幣方面想誒問一啲問題㗎。就誒裏邊誒，我想知道你哋而家嗰個初步考慮係去都係同香港嘅銀根供應係同一體係啊？個本位制度係咪都同而家？
唔該，主席。嗱，其實誒，我哋公佈咧，即係大約我諗兩個星期前啦。我哋公佈就會作呢個研究。嗱，噉我哋第一階段嘅研究咧，其實係多數着重喺技術嗰方面多少少嘅嚇。咁誒，我都講過話，譬如金融穩定啊、貨幣政策咧，呢個我哋喺初步都會誒做少少研究，但係唔會。
會太深入住，因為我哋而家睇見係其他國家咧，我諗超過十個地方啦，十個央行咧喺唔同嘅階段咧都作出一啲研究嘅，而大部分咧都因為區塊鏈個發展得好快啦，都睇一睇區塊鏈呢個科技會唔會引申可以有個契機去睇一睇央行發行呢個數碼貨幣嚇。咁其實好誒。
好多都係由一個技術嘅層面去出發先嚇，咁所以頭先你問嘅問題咧，呢個我哋要逐步階段去睇嘅。而家我哋係太早，我哋唔會去到咁快去決定好多嘅嘢，而我哋亦都冇計劃做或者唔做第一階段咧。去到今年年底咧，去做一個研究先。我哋最緊要研究就係你。
瞭解到呢個科技嗰個應用性係咪真係可行？第一，第二究竟有咩好處？真係誒，而家我哋睇到好多地方講出嚟嘅都係啲概念上嘅好處啦。但係我哋根本都唔係好完全瞭解得到，所以我哋要做一啲概念認證先嚇。咁嗱，但係個分別係噉啊嘛。誒，其他央行。
因為佢哋唔係誒實施聯係匯率咧，佢哋當然冇嗰啲憂慮啦。佢嗰個銀根供應咧，佢哋可以有中央銀行自己去做控制啊嘛。但係香港行嘅聯係匯率咧，實體貨幣裏邊其實係一套係都幾複雜同埋都幾特別嘅一個系統嚟嘅。咁而家你用數碼貨幣咧？
究竟你係喺呢個系統以外係不受聯係匯率監管，定話你翻翻入去聯係匯率嗰個制度裏邊係需要用嚇美元去兑換啦噉樣咁裏邊亦都牽涉到就係個流速會影響到整個誒貨幣供應同埋通貨膨脹個控制嘅問題，所以誒希望啦，即係你做研究嘅時候。
可能都要都要特別針對呢一方面，避免即係到時就係技術可行啊，技術好可行啊，可能好大幫助，但係佢對嗰個聯係匯率嘅衝擊嗰度，可能係另一個危機都唔定。明白，李生係唔該主席。明白嘅，我哋喺個研究裏邊，誒嗱，我哋第一階段我諗技術。
啊！多謝啊，主席。咁其實咧就睇到啊，政府自從去年十一月就即係嗰個支付系統及儲值支付工具條例生效之後啦。噉就正如文件所講咧，亦都拍出咗誒批出咗十三個牌照㗎啦。噉我都覺得呢個的而且確係踏出咗重要嘅一步嘅。咁喺度咧，我就。
想問誒有啲問題咧，就係第一啊，目前有冇進一步嘅考量咧？即係拍咗批咗呢十三個牌照之後，有冇評估過嗰個業界嘅需求，將來仲有機會拍多啲嘅牌照出嚟？誒，呢個係第一樣嘢啦。第二樣嘢咧就係因為我我自己本身唔係搞科技嘅，所以我唔係好清楚，就想問。
問一問誒呢啲牌照批咗出嚟，啲公司咧，我想問下佢哋嗰啲科技嘅系統係咪？如果用咗某一隻系統之後，另外一隻系統就唔可能進場嘅咧？嗱，我我咁問，因為主要就意思即係話會唔會係有一種系統？如果用開咗呢一隻新入場嘅嘅人士或者公
誒。
好，最後係葉劉淑儀議員。
平等嘅平台，佢哋比比較佢哋嘅服務啦，佢哋嘅嘅創新啊。
用依啲新嘅誒一啲服務咧，係比較個信心更加大嘅。噉我哋會會喺一年會去睇。
誒而家咧，我見到文件裏面第八段咧都講過咧，就係話其實誒有過往都有我哋呢個會嘅委員係問過嘅，即係未來五到十年係咪真係可以將香港轉型成為一個無現金社會，或者我哋嗰個誒政府嘅運作可唔可以率先係開始帶領？
去做呢一啲用呢啲金融嘅科技咧，咁因為我亦都見到即係誒今次文件亦都講啦，誒明年就會推出嗰個快速支付系統啦。噉我覺得呢個係好重要一步嚟嘅。噉我就想問埋啦，呢個快速支付系統因為係將來咧，我見到文件講咧，亦都係跨銀行嘅，即係全部唔同銀行都一齊同。
統一用咁呢個係咪就係一個將來會一個統一嘅系統，無論銀行或者所有嘅其他嘅支付公司都要follow呢一套噉嘅系統嘅咧？我就想問埋呢個問題啫。啊，唔該，主席，係啊，秘書長，誒，我請李生答答我嗰幾題關於支付系統嘅事。好啊，阿李生，O.K.嗱噉。
我我嘗試總合去去講講啦，嗱嗰啲誒儲值支付工具啦，我哋發咗十三個牌照，係仲有一啲公司同我哋傾緊嘅，仲有公司有興趣嘅。咁其實誒，我諗都我都問過有個別公司咧，我都幾誒覺得幾奇，點解香港可以容納咁多咩？嗱，其實幾得意，因為香港係一個國際金。
中心咧有誒幾大部分係中國內地嘅供應商嚟香港，想攞個牌照。噉我哋同佢傾嗰時咧，佢係想用香港作一個平台去走出去嘅嚇。咁喺呢度攞咗個國際監管嘅經驗之後咧，佢走出去國際噉樣噉。佢聽外國嚟香港攞牌噉，我點解你唔去其他東南嘅國家啊？有啲誒。
誒誒，可能都可以適合喎。噉佢哋同我哋講咧，好多都話咧，因為中國大陸嘅市場，所以佢覺得香港一個好好嘅平台嗱。所以我哋吸引咗嗱。如果你有數字睇翻，我我唔講其他國家啦。東南亞咧應該冇咁多呢啲所謂儲值支付工具落牌，除咗中國大陸。中國大陸係講二百幾間。O.K.嗱噉。
噉你話會唔會排他咧？嗱，如果科技上咧，我嘅認知咧就唔應該會排他嘅。甚至我哋嗰個誒Fast Payment嗰個即時支付系統咧，其實我哋更加想有一個平台咧，畀一個平台呢啲支付供應商同埋銀行一齊喺個平台裏邊發展支付。而到時下年推出嗰時候咧，呢啲。
主席，我好快誒誒，關於係咪行cashless society，即係一一依個問題咧。實在而家即係誒今今年喺依個財政預算案，財政司長講咗咧，我哋會誒為咗推依個金融科技咧，我會檢視政府係可以接受啲唔同嘅支付。
付工具嘅誒誒誒誒，即係政府服務方面嘅收費咧，可唔可以多啲用？而家政府嘅收費咧，根本係有超過一半咧，係已經唔係用現金交付㗎啦，即係大部分係電誒網上啊，或者E E嘅誒嘅。
渠道去做誒支付嘅，我哋希望咧就喺嚟緊呢年咧，我哋去研究咧，可唔可以而家多咗，即係李生講多咗咁多呢啲唔同嘅流動支付嘅嘅模式咧？政府可唔可以亦都開放我哋喺收費方面咧，係收到用到呢啲，令到市民對於用。
啊！多謝主席。噉就頭先各位誒同事都誒，我哋都討論過指出，如果講純粹金融科技嘅企業咧嚇，初創發展，深圳嗰啲即係比香港蓬勃啦，係嘛？對企業嘅發展嚟講蓬勃嘅，但係金融科技嘅發
發展咧的，而且確頭先梁繼昌議員都講過，好多專家指出咧，長遠會對於金融業用嘅人手好有衝擊嘅，係嘛？譬如即係有專家即係我都唔係咁識嘅啲專家同我講啦嚇，用block chain嚇，即係呢個分佈式咩帳目。
呢個就哦。
啊！嗰啲商科學院嗰啲院長傾下。
同埋咧，政府點樣利用金融科技？
做嗰陣時係做得比較方便，做得比較個成本低一啲，但係同時間咧，我哋都要要求咧係要做到係我哋都可以順納依個KYC係真真正正做咗嘅。
然後而家做緊中介依啲嘅佢份工仲有冇喺度？即係嗰啲就算嗰啲風險管理計數嗰啲幸運機器都可以取代啊！即係我建議誒財經局咧都要快啲同我哋啲大學傾下。
去發展市場，你就去嗰個投資者嘅地方同我開户口；一就佢翻嚟香港，飛過嚟香港同我哋開户口。嗱呢個咧完全咧冇利用到金融科技嘅好處。噉我想啊問問政府到底擔心呢個係乜嘢問題咧？
依依個係監管機構要要負責嘅，或者我我我嗱，啲政府啊督促佢啊嘛，提咗我我翻去跟進啦。依個好噉啊，多謝呢個環節已經結束，多謝政府啊嘅介紹，唔該。
嗰個嗰個東西嚇區塊鏈，我知嚇，即係而家已經有一個叫ethereum嘅嚇，可以網上做好多交易啊、合同啊、電子簽名啊。將來中介人都唔需要，少好多中介人。仲有譬如話買賣股票咁用algorithm trading，其實而家都有啲分。
真係做㗎啦，咁將來亦都唔使人手大筆algorithm做啊，得㗎啦。咁仲有啲machine learning嗰啲咧，長遠我唔係講話兩三年啦，我再耐啲咧，可能令到香港咧中層或者前台好多人手流失，唔需要啊。呢個其實科技衝擊啊～
企業咧係已經全世界發生緊啦。政府有啲乜嘢準備咧？除咗支支即係支持嗰啲初創嘅企業搞FinTech之外，對於金融人手嗰個manpower嘅安排預測同埋培訓，點樣嘅咩準備？李司長唔該，主席誒誒，議員提嗰個係一個。
即係好大嘅問題係係需要我哋去睇。我哋同各個金融行業都有開始傾，就係對於尤其是將來一啲中介嘅服務嘅影響會係點？即係阿葉議員講得啱，因為譬如而家好多中介嘅服務咧，係將來係咪可以透過金融科技？
全部嘅中介人都唔需要咧，咁譬如我哋亦都有開始同誒誒保險業界傾啦，業界嘅睇法咧就都有好好大嘅參差。啊，秘書長，我呢啲長者係實需要嘅，但係嗰啲年輕人咧，即係越嚟越識玩科技咧，一路嚟嗰啲越嚟越多。唔係淨係長者嘅，因為有好多。
咧誒，始終去到產品嘅介紹，即係譬如保險產品嘅介紹誒。依啲咧誒，我哋同好多業界講咧，佢哋覺得未來就算長遠五年後咧，依啲都唔會完全係會取替曬全部中介啊。咁但係當然誒，議員提嗰個問題就比較我哋要心願要去留。
咁咧就係我哋喺即係培訓方面，我哋係要開始同業界傾咧，係咪某一啲嘅誒，尤其是喺金融科技依一方面嘅多啲依方面嘅知識咧，可以畀到而家現職嘅人，等佢哋增加佢哋將來嗰個競爭力咧。因為我哋擔心嘅就係五年後十。
好，最後我都有少少個問題，我想問啊，秘書長啊，即係個我哋用咗四億元嘅美金咧去發展啊金融創新科技，比呢個澳洲、日本、新加坡都多嘅。噉我知道咧，頭先講政府都講過咧，做咗唔少嘅功夫，亦都組織一個促進。
啊！辦公室啊，金融科技促進辦公室，但係咧有冇考慮到即係呢幾年嘅成果如何咧？即係關於個證券投資、金融科技嗰方面，證券嗰方面又有乜嘢創新咧？嗱，我舉個好簡單嘅例子，即係上一年咧，證監委已經誒發出通告，容許我哋做。
網上嘅認證噉啊，而我咧同創科局熟下嘅智慧城市同埋郵政局，亦都簽過幾次，亦都同意咗嗰個技術可以可以誒可以認可嘅。但係咧，政府一次次都未批，受到好多嘅掣肘。而家我哋去開户口咧，一係你就。
徹底實實在在咧，即係我哋所需嘅呢個開户嘅呢個呢個方式咧，可以落實咧。唔該。誒，主席，你你都知誒，依個SFC同埋業界呢一類有就住呢個問題傾。頭先阿莫拉公員問我，我我哋又講SFC實在佢哋有做睇緊，但唔同層面嘅嘢就係所謂我哋。
權力。
係。
有。
或者我。
係第一版出現。
啊！
啊！多謝主席。
啊，首先。
佢會，佢會跳㗎啦。
我哋呢個五安都有㗎。
係我哋而家咧就講緊咧金融機構處置機制嘅條例，噉啊，請我哋嘅政府啊邊一位介紹一下，簡單下。
誒金融機構處置機制條例咧，其實喺誒舊年六月咧，立法會已經通過咗，噉就係為受涵蓋嘅金融機構咧設立一個跨界別嘅處置機制。
誒多謝主席。首先誒，我會簡單咁介紹一下誒受保障安排規例嗰個背景，跟住我會請誒金管局嘅同事亦都好簡單咁講一講誒呢一個規例裏邊誒嗰個主要嘅建議嘅。
制定嘅附屬法例，咁個目的就係為咗喺處置行動中咧，我哋要保障一啲主要嘅金融安排嘅經濟效益。噉我哋就住啊保障安排規例咧。
而家話係regulation technology，即係佢哋想應用呢啲新嘅科技咧，令到喺監管上邊咧可以方便咗。咁呢個頭先主席提嘅問題就正正而家證監佢哋喺度睇緊有邊啲方面喺監管市場方面，佢哋可以利用到最新嘅金融科技。
令到無論係即係誒依個服務提供者或者接受服務嘅人，可以更加方便嘅噉。所以剛才提嘅誒，政監係研究緊，佢哋希望咧，但最最重要就係有一個比較穩妥嘅方法，因為頭先直提咧，依個就係你即係所謂我哋K Y C誒。
每每開新户口、新嘅客人都要做嘅K Y C嘅過程咧，我哋要即係起碼都可以信納咧。呢個K Y C係做嘅做到而家即係我哋嘅規例上嘅要求嘅。咁所以即係當然，我希望咧，將來大家可以透過科技K Y C做。
誒，秘書長，你都知道咧，個書牌咧入邊有一個條例，即雙方政府認可嘅文件咧，就係成立嘅。咁所以咧，我哋誒即通過呢個郵政局去認證國內嘅客户，而國內嘅客户係由嗰個公安部認認可嘅。噉樣都你都唔可以。
認為呢個已經係足夠嘞？咩嗱？而家一帶一路大灣區咧，即係如火如荼嘅。咁如果再拖落去咧，啲客户都畀人攞曬，我哋去發展進入呢個呢個大亞區都大灣區都對我哋都冇大幫助啦。係咪？你係咪要盡快解決呢個問題？誒。
咁處置條例嗰個主要目的咧，就係為咗符合啊金融穩定理事會誒制定嘅有效金融機構處置機制主要元素裏邊嘅國際標準，為咗誒一啲唔可以持續經營但係又有系統重要性嘅金融機構咧，提供一啲處置所需嘅。
咁而事實上喺好多個司法嘅管轄區咧，譬如英國啦、美國啦，或者歐盟成員國咧，其實都已經根據主要元素咧設立咗金融處置機制㗎啦。噉我哋今次同誒委員誒介紹嘅咧，其實就係根據處置條例第七十五條。
Thank you, Mr Chairman.
Okay，Mr. White。
These carve-outs or exclusions are defined narrowly.
The Protected Arrangements Regulations provide a broad protection to these counterparties in resolution.
咁誒，我哋亦都喺咧四月六號咧發表咗誒嘅誒發表咗諮詢總結㗎啦。
一份嘅意見書，分別嚟自業界組織啦、專業團體同埋金融市場基建。
意見之後咧，亦都會採納當中一啲建議，令到我哋呢一個受保障安排咧係更加完善嘅。
However, in using the resolution tools, bank counterparties need to understand how they will be treated in advance to avoid contagion to funding markets in a resolution event.
保護安排條例是設計，使得決算機構應以一種方式行使其權力，以保障保護金融安排決算的經濟效果。
立法會進行先定立後審議嘅程序，令到兩者咧都可以喺今年之內生效嘅。噉我而家誒想請金管局嘅同事誒介紹一下受保障安排誒規例嘅主要建議。
The key point is that the protection provided by these regulations is designed to restrict the resolution authority on use of the stabilisation powers in the event of a future bank failure.
However, certain carve-outs or exclusions are defined under these regulations to enable the resolution authority to ensure Hong Kong financial stability on use of the resolution tools and continuity in the core banking functions.
這是因為當一家系統性銀行失敗時，解決機構必須使用其解決工具，以維持香港金融穩定，並保護關鍵銀行功能的連續性，例如存款。
其實較早前，我哋已經連同誒金管局啦、誒保險業監督啦，同埋證監會咧，係進行咗維期兩個月嘅公眾諮詢。噉我哋喺諮詢期間咧，同主要嘅持份者見過面啊，亦都聽過佢哋嘅意見。喺誒諮詢完結嘅時候咧，我哋總共係收到十。
啊！咁回應啊，回應我哋呢個諮詢文件啊啊嗰啲回應者咧，其實啊，普遍都同意我哋喺諮詢文件裏邊提出點樣處理受保障安排嘅做法啊，而且咧，佢哋亦都提出咗一啲啊建設性啦、技術性嘅意見。噉我哋喺考慮過呢一啲意。
誒，我哋而家嗰個時間表咧，就會諗住係喺啊完成受保障安排規例先定立後審議嘅程序之後咧，處置條例咧亦都會隨之而生效。我哋將會喺今年嘅第二季將受保障安排規例同埋處置條例嘅生效公告咧提交誒嚟。
This protection comes with a range of carve-outs or exclusions designed to achieve two outcomes.
一清盤及結算系統安排是安排，under一 recognised clearinghouse 或一 designated clearing and settlement system。
和，
Confidence for financial market participants that critical risk mitigation funding techniques will be protected, with certainty and predictability.
And second, an appropriate degree of flexibility for the resolution authority to exercise their powers in order to achieve orderly resolution.
所以，The Protected Arrangements Regulations are important because financial market participants rely on such protected arrangements as risk mitigation tools and as financing sources.
So, turning to protected the partial property transfer, and the treatment of clearing and settlement systems arrangements. This slide describes the protected arrangements approach to these financial arrangements.
作為結果，《保護安排條例》是結構圍繞這兩個決議工具。我將先處理部分財產轉移，接著是賠償，最後解釋違反《保護安排條例》的後果。
So in terms of what financial arrangements are defined under the protected arrangements, there are six in total: clearing and settlement systems arrangements, secured arrangements, structured finance arrangements, and set-off, netting and title transfer arrangements.
The protected arrangements regulations are designed to provide the appropriate degree of protection for financial market participants and banks' counterparties on the exercise of the resolution authority's tools, for example, a bail-in or a partial property transfer, in the event of a future bank failure.
通過，which some but not all of the entity's assets, rights and liabilities are transferred to a third party, or on a bail-in, where liabilities are written down or converted without taking into account linked assets or rights entitled to be set off or netted under documented agreements.
Given the objective of the protected arrangements regulation, it is the view it is our view that the risk of economic effect of a protected arrangement being undermined is most likely to occur, firstly either in a partial property transfer is made by the resolution authority.
The specific arrangements of a recognised clearing house or a designated clearing and settlement system that should not be disrupted is in a partial property transfer are those protected by the insolvency override in the SFO and the PSSVFO respectively.
under under the proposed protections, the resolution authority is to seek to transfer all but not some of assets, rights or liabilities of an entity that are part of a clearing and settlement system's arrangements to the extent that not to do so would disrupt the operation of the clearing and settlement system arrangement.
examples of these arrangements include recognised clearinghouses, set-off and netting of rights and liabilities under counterparty with a counterparty under a master agreement, secured financing arrangements, securitisations like a covered bond programme, and repurchase transactions.
即。
Turning to secured financing arrangements, this slide describes the proposed protection.
There was broad support in the consultation response for protected arrangements treatment of secured arrangements.
和同埋，同前一節提到的外國財產條款，也適用於這些保護。
An exclusion is defined under the protected arrangements as as it applies to structured finance arrangements.
這 is necessary to ensure continuity of access to deposits for customers and counterparties through the resolution.
In this case, the exclusion means that deposits can be transferred separately from the securitisation.
首先，《保護安排條例》適用於一類結構化金融安排，即為結構化金融安排。
Under the proposed protection, the resolution authority should not transfer all, but not some of the of the constituent parts of a secured arrangement.
This slide describes the protected arrangements approach to secured arrangements, an example being a secured financing arrangement.
Under the protection, the resolution authority should transfer all, but not some, of the assets, rights and liabilities which form part of a structured finance arrangement.
And for the final section on partial property transfer, this slide describes the protected arrangements proposed approach to set-off, netting and title transfers arrangements.
However, if financial property forming part of a secured arrangement is unable to be effectively transferred under the transfer instrument, this would not be deemed to be inconsistent with the objectives of the Protected Arrangements Regulations.
這條款關係到香港法例的執行力範圍，而雖然會盡力確保所有資產、權利和義務轉移，這是非常必要，以確保香港的金融穩定受到保護。
the protection described sets out the resolutionary should not transfer all but not some of the rights and liabilities that may be set off or netted under a set off netting and title transfer arrangement that are documented or otherwise evidenced in writing.
Generally, the consultation response was broadly supportive of our proposed approach, and our final proposed approach in developing the regulations is to further specify the definitions and link the definition of structured finance arrangements to securitisation.
In terms of the consultation process, feedback from consultation respondents was broadly positive, with some refining comments on the scope and definitions used to define clearing and settlement system arrangements. Our our proposed response is to broaden the definition to align with the SFO and the PSSV.
receive receivables owed by depositors.
This concludes the section on partial property transfer, and I turn to bail-in.
The same provision, foreign property provision, as mentioned previously, also applies in this case.
The exclusions defined are liabilities arising from any capital instrument or subordinated debt or unsecured debt instrument.
The rights and liabilities excluded from the protections and set-off netting and title transfer arrangements include deposits.
不secured liabilities, deposits not excluded from bail-in and liabilities relating to claims for damages or award of damages or claims under indemnity.
子ordinated debt, transferable securities, operating rights and liabilities, and an award of damages or claims under an indemnity.
This is important to ensure that the resolution authority has sufficient flexibility in a partial property transfer to ensure Hong Kong financial stability.
Unsecured liabilities arising from an instrument or contract, at at its issuance date, had a maturity a residual maturity of over 12 months, and is not a financial contract.
There are a range of exclusions defined under the protected arrangements, and these are particular necessary to protect taxpayers by ensuring the ability of the resolution authority to impose losses on the bank's creditors.
The protected regions regulations proposes a set of exclusions necessary to ensure continuity in the banking services through the resolution and to protect Hong Kong taxpayers.
In addition, clauses which provide for walkaway or a broad sweeper clause under set-off and netting or title transfer arrangements would not be treated as part of a protected arrangement.
General feedback from consultation respondents was supportive of our approach to protected areas as it applies to Baling. There were some minor comments around definitions, which we have reflected to align our definitions in response to consultation feedback.
The proposed protection sets out that the resolution authorities should only make bail-in provisions in respect of the net amount that an entity in resolution and its counterparties are entitled by contract to set off or net under a set-off arrangement, netting arrangement or a title transfer arrangement.
所以這張幻燈片描述了保護安排的approach to Basel，而因為Basel決議不會影響結算和清算系統、受保障安排或結構化安排，保護安排條例只處理Basel決議下的抵銷、淨值和標的物轉移安排。
所以諮詢回應是廣泛支持我們的方案，提出了一個關於文件的問題，我們在諮詢回應中有所反映，我們也澄清了保護協議的目標是確保行業標準的主協議受到保護。
啊。
liabilities.
Thank you.
does not arise.
And finally.
Under a clearing settlement system, transactions were disrupted.
和受影響的 parties， 和確保他們的立場得到恢復。
However, if inadvertent action is taken due to, for example, poor financial institution information.
這個後果的幻燈片使決議草案能夠處理那對影響財政安排的影響。
這張幻燈片描述了行動所產生的後果，由決議機構採取，與保護安排的目標不一致。
For a secured arrangement and a structured finance arrangement, the affected party's position may be restored by the resolution authority through the exercise of a supplemental or a reverse transfer power.
And finally, with respect to bail-in and the treatment of set-off, netting and title transfer arrangements, if there is an inconsistent treatment on use of resolution tools by the resolution authority, the affected party's position may be restored by appropriate measures set by the resolution authority.
我哋想清楚，我們將此視為一個後備條款，並非預期會在BAU或正常使用決議工具時依賴。然而，我們認為妥當釐清若出現工具誤用時，可能面臨嘅後果。就權力目標而言。
Firstly, the resolution authority through resolution planning in peacetime will aim to avoid any risk of inconsistent use of resolution powers with respect to protected arrangements by aiming to identify relevant contracts so that this this issue.
So the protections differ under each protected arrangements, and I'll just step through them very quickly. Under if there's an inconsistent treatment of clearing and settlement systems under the protected arrangement subject in a partial transfer, that would be void to the extent that the transfer of some, but not all of the related assets, rights and
就係，就
阿石禮謙嚇。
Thank you, Chairman. Thank you for the question.
啊，Mr. White。
我話陳志磊誒，陳志英議員咧。
好，就呢個問題誒，要發言嘅語言整登記。
仲有邊位？而家暫時咧就有兩位陳振英、阿石禮謙同埋我哋副主席梁繼昌。
同交易誒可以按我哋香港嘅法例做咧。如果有一啲地區其實係未立相應嘅法律嘅，咁喺我哋實施呢個誒處置條例嗰時咧，會唔會有任何嘅障礙咧？嚇，唔該，主席。啊，郭女士。啊。
That was consistent with the protected arrangements provisions set out in the BRD. In terms of the implications for creditors or the stakeholders of the institution, the resolution authorities in Portugal, my understanding was they acted to establish a bridge bank.
And transferred the vast majority of the bank's assets and liability, the good assets and deposit liabilities to that bridge bank, leaving behind in the residual rump entity some of the unsecured and capital instruments on the bank's balance sheet.
唔該，主席。誒，呢個金融機構處置機制嘅條例咧，就係處理香港誒如果有不可持續經營同埋具系統性重要嘅金融機構，如果可能倒閉嘅情況之下咧，提供一個替代嘅破產清盤程序嘅辦法啦，我嚟保障香港金融系統穩定同埋有效運作。
噉啊，等金融機構嘅股東同債權人承擔虧損就保障公堂嘅。咁喺文件裏邊咧有兩個問題。第一個咧就係佢提到咧誒呢個噉嘅機制咧係參考英國採用嘅做法，同埋用歐盟嘅銀行恢復同埋處置指令作為藍本。
去草議嘅噉，我想問下英國同歐盟咧有冇執行呢一類處置機制嘅先例作為參考？咁究竟有冇對其他嘅誒唔同嘅stickholder有影響咧？咁呢個係第一個問題。第二個問題咧就係誒作為處理呢啲香港金融機構出現不可持續經營嘅程序安排嘅。
時候咧，一定會涉及其他司法管轄區嘅同業交易，即係譬如其他國家香港成立嘅分行啦。噉佢誒呢啲交易嘅時候咧，涉及呢啲交易嘅時候咧，其他司法管轄區咧係咪需要同樣立法嚟確保咧？佢哋會配合我哋香港呢啲噉嘅金融。
Taking the first question in terms of any precedents in the European Union with respect to the use of the resolution tools, it's right to say that there are low number, low single digit numbers of bank failure in the European Union. In recent history, after the passage
Of the B or D, there have been one or two examples in Europe of bank failure. One case in Portugal where the resolution authorities used the partial property transfer resolution powers. And my understanding is that those powers were applied in a manner.
And in terms of taking your second question respect to cross border resolution transactions, while the financial institutions resolution ordinance sets out a range of objectives for the resolution authorities in Hong Kong, that reflects the fact that Hong Kong is an open and international banking.
啊，有冇跟進？
Sure. Yeah. And and I think.
都係講落出去嘅，多謝啊，主席。
and that we see that as a precondition for ensuring financial stability in Hong Kong.
冇噉樣做，咁或者誒嗰個詳細嗰個情況，我請金管局嘅同事誒解釋一下。
Worth mentioning a number of additional comments that were also raised as part of the consultation response, and I'll just take them in turn.
Some other small points that we received in terms of feedback were about the sweeper or walkaway clauses and the importance of ensuring that
Specificity to the definition of clearing and settlement systems, mapping it directly to the SFO and the PSSVFO, to make it more explicit the high level of protection that is provided to clearing and settlement systems in resolution.
Sector, so while the resolution authorities in Hong Kong will be developing resolution plans for entities in Hong Kong, that can also include coordinated cross-border resolution strategies and resolution plans with foreign authorities. We see this as important to address the very point you're raising about branch activities.
或大型entities of foreign banks operating in Hong Kong， and that's why， for for example over the last four or five years the Hong Kong MA has been working through FSB's crisis management groups to develop resolution plans and make big cross-border banks more resolvable.
我啊，第二位啊，石禮謙議員，多謝主主席。頭先啊，秘書長咧就講喺呢個諮詢時間嗰陣時咧，佢哋都收咗好多嘅意見。噉佢哋有啲意見就接受咗喺個報告誒，畀我哋頭先嗰份文件咧，我睇唔到。
即係有啲意見，你哋係唔接受嗰啲意見。依家唔接受嘅意見係點解咧？係點解冇去擺入嚟依度裏邊咧？同埋係影響到香港嘅金融中心各方面係乜嘢咧？同埋影響嗰啲stickholders嗰方面係係點咧？即係往往好多政府嘅文件。
咧只係報喜不報喪嘅啫嚇，咁咧你就係喺依方面咧，我想了解下清楚啲。如果我哋係有一個negative weighting嘅，我亦都知道有其他嘅意見係咪咁重要，而係唔重要。所以我好希望咧，將來你擺啲諮詢嘅文，擺啲文件入嚟咧，係兩方面。
啊，邊攞回應咧？係誒，或者我誒簡單講一講先。其實咧，我哋喺文件嗰個第十段嗰度都有講過咧。其實有一啲回應就希望我哋咧將自動化交易服務咧嘅結算安排都包括喺我哋呢個受保障安排規例裏邊嘅。噉我哋都解釋咗點解咧，我哋。
We received some comments about on definitional issues. So in our consultation, we set out an approach to defining financial contracts, and also we defined derivative contracts. Some of the consultation response received noted some overlap in the definitions. So we have since
Taken that feedback and expanded our definition of financial contracts to encompass derivative contracts, and also to with respect to clearing and settlement systems, we have also taken on board feedback from the consultation response to more clearly define and add additional specific.
嗯。
The Hong Kong regime.
to include be able to evidence in writing. So again, I think this was a helpful feedback from industry, and we were able to incorporate it.
Is there a mechanism to reverse that kind of transfer? Is it dealt with in in the regulation? My two questions, yeah.
嘅嘅附屬法例，即係《Loss Absorption Regulation》。咁所以誒，呢一個就係會我哋下一步做嘅工作。但係首先，我哋覺得最重要就係受保障安排規例先，係。
Does it need to perfect this transfer if the asset is situated in Hong Kong, or vice versa? If we do not think the universal succession transfer is a good idea under...
what the protected arrangements regulation specify. So what we're trying to do with the protected arrangements regulations is to recognise if there is a piece of foreign property as part of a secured arrangement or securitisation, that for whatever reason the transfer of which is frustrated by a foreign court.
Protected Arrangement Regulation is the only piece of subsidiary legislation which would enable the financial institution resolution regime to enable to to operate. Or do you have other regulations in the pipeline? That's my first question.
Industry master agreements, for example, ISDA agreements, will be protected through the resolution, and that are included by the protection under protected arrangements. So we've taken steps to reflect that comment as well, and specified that clearly in this paper for FAP, but also in our consultation response. And the last point I'd mention was around the requirement.
Requirement to have financial contracts written, or at least be able to evidence in writing. This was a slight difference from approaches taken in other jurisdictions. However, following comments received as part of the consultation, we expanded our approach to defining the requirement on written contracts.
誒同埋補充下誒，我哋都同意阿石誒石議員嘅意見。我哋下次如果喺誒文件嗰度咧，都可能兩方面意見，我哋都誒多啲鋪排。咁可能誒就會有個誒，即係再全面啲嗰個嗰個表誒表表達出嚟，可能再全面一啲。即係主席，即係我哋做一個立法者，我哋有個責任。
去睇曬啲依啲噉嘅條例，係咪對香港整體嘅發展喺金融發展、金金融穩定嗰方面好？所以我哋即係有彼得，你要叻嗰啲writing，我哋都要有支持喺度。多謝主席啦。好，下一位係梁繼昌。I've got two questions. The one I just want to know whether the
My second question is: Does the PAR deals with deals with conflict of law issue? What I'm talking about is, for example, in transfer of assets scenario, if a foreign jurisdiction recognises the concept of universal succession.
係噉。
係。
Commissioner White.
屬於結構式金融安排咧。
就建議係全部，而非部分。
係屬於呢個誒結構式金融安排嘅咧。
O.K.下一位係誒姚崇源誒議員。
哇！唔該，主席。誒，就首先第一咧，我見到文卷裏邊誒，好著意提到就係話。
轉讓呢個，我想問下裏邊嗰個考慮係點解要全部而唔係局部啦？咁另外第二個部分咧就係誒。
for globally systemically important banks. So there are a range of potential barriers which we are working to address through that, to identify and work together with other authorities to remove them to ensure that the cross-border strategies are feasible and credible.
of the tools and which are necessary to protect Hong Kong financial stability, so we see that as a kind of an important provision, but within the protected arrangements. In terms of sort of cross-border recognition on use of the wider transfer tools or bail-in powers, I think there are potential barriers to
係誒，我或者誒講咗第一誒，我係答咗第一條先，跟住請金管總同事答第二條。咁誒，其實誒，我哋都係覺得咧誒，首先係要做咗受保障安排規例咧誒，先至可以令到處置條例生效，因為誒提供咗一個法律上嘅確定性，就一啲好主要嘅金融安排咧。
係受到保障嘅，咁誒跟住落嚟咧，誒處置條例同埋受保障規例生效咗之後咧，其實我哋下一步誒都已經係誒準備會做其他喺法例誒下邊嘅附屬法例嘅，譬如我哋下一個誒誒有計劃做嘅咧，就係嗰個誒吸納虧損能力。
Thank you, Mr. White. And turning to the the second question about conflict of law issues, I think there are there are two is two parts of the question. One of which is relevant for the protected arrangements regulations, and then the second part I think is more about the challenges and barriers to applying the resolution tools in the event of a failure beyond.
That does not frustrate the application of the transfer by the Hong Kong authorities, and this is important because if there was a one piece of foreign property as part of a very large portfolio of in a secured arrangement or an securitisation, this could become a significant barrier to the application.
orderly implementation of cross-border resolution strategies, either led by Hong Kong or where Hong Kong is a host participant in a cross-border resolution strategy. But I think these are the types of issues that we work to identify as part of cross-border resolution planning. For an example of which is the crisis management groups.
裏邊可能係咪即係包括好多誒？可能係迷你債啊、accumulator、CDO、CDS，當呢一啲喺喺crisis嘅時候，如果出現大量負債而去又做轉讓，咁嗰個誒安全同埋嗰個負債嗰個確保係誒會係點樣處理？
The important part of keeping a structured financial arrangement together, like a securitisation in a partial property transfer, is to reflect how that arrangement operates in peacetime or on a B A U basis. So a pool of assets will be dedicated to the structured finance.
arrangement， and that that arrangement will then issue securities to the market， off the back off the back of the earnings that will be provided for by the assets in the the fixed pool， so an example of this would be a covered bond programme， so if the resolution authority on entry of the bank into resolution
was to break that apart.
Well, it seems to to have a lot of discretion.
Asset， so would it have the negative impact then？
O.K. 最後一位係周浩鼎議員。
As because that's an important part of how banks fund themselves and how the financial markets operate.
所以我們認為非常重要，要保護承銷人，承銷人。
Transfering the deposits, that this this is what ensures continuity of access to those deposits.
to give them confidence that if a structured finance arrangement like a covered bond programme enters a resolution, the resolution authority will not break it break it apart and deny them access to their security.
and transfer some but not all of the assets in the structured finance arrangement. That would significantly impact the quality of the securities that had been sold to the market.
所以它它depends on the resolution strategy and depends on the firms that is failing at the time. It may be the case that it's considered consistent with the resolution objectives to leave the entire securitisation in the rump to enter into a winding up.
And then how about the deposit? You mentioned that it would be excluded. Is it a must or also a flexibility of the RA? Similarly, it's a flexibility and it depends on the situation at the time. The reason for this particular exclusion is because by trans
唔該，嗯，Well， first of all， I think I do welcome this sort of new arrangement to rescue the financial institutions in case of their failure to make sure that there would be a financial stability for the city. But I just want to make sure that if the ordinance takes effect.
equally, it may be considered consistent with the resolution objectives to transfer the secured arrangement as a whole to a bridge bank or to a private sector purchaser. I think what the regulations are making clear is that we are not allowed to break them apart, and they need to remain whole.
So, like our one of the primary objectives in a partial transfer resolution is to ensure continuity of access to depositors, and if there are any deposits sitting in the securitisation, it's very important that the securitisation also has access to those deposits.
誒，姚燕，你有冇跟進咧？仲有少少時間。係啊，呢啲係second part of my question。Could you repeat the second part again? Yeah.誒，of course you have mentioned about in peacetime. Yes, I agree. But in crisis time, then say for example those CDO and CDS right would be included in right the誒誒the whole package of.
I think it would it would depend on the circumstances at the time, and I think that what the protected arrangements regulations make clear is that there is no requirement on the resolution authority to transfer or to leave behind the structured finance arrangement. Sorry, no. There is no requirement to transfer.
係。
嗯。
Okay. Thank you.
Good morning. Thank you, Chairman.
好，我哋請政府官員入嚟。
因為這是個聯合consultation，我會做一個聯合presentation。
誒好啊！我哋而家請政府官員介紹啊，簡單五分鐘時間，唔該。
好，我哋呢個誒議題就到呢度為止，多謝政府官員嚇。
then there would be no more winding up procedures to be applicable upon these financial institutions. I just want to clarify. There's only one way to deal with this sort of failure. So no more winding up procedures.
judged systemic, then we can block the winding up and instead consider entry into resolution. If it's judged non-systemic, so you can imagine a very very small institution, then we would we would not block the entry into winding up.
Right, so yeah, let me take that. So in terms of the scope of the FIR, it covers all financial institutions. However, the judgement about which institutions will enter the resolution regime will depend on whether they are considered systemic at the point of failure.
So there there's a hurdle for entry into the resolution regime, which is you must present a risk to financial stability. So I will assume that if the the so-called financial institutions falls within the scope, within the protection under this ordinance, there will be no more winding up procedures to be applicable on these.
financial institutions，所以 in case， for example， the reason why I ask this question is in case when you have this ordinance to be applicable on these financial institutions， all of a sudden somebody just simply turn up to file winding up application， there would be conflict， isn't it？ But that won't happen， isn't it？ I just want to clarify。
That's correct. So there's a process set out in the financial institutions resolution ordinance for notification of the resolution authority on presentation of a winding up petition. Okay. So that allows the authorities time to consider whether this institution is systemic or non-systemic. If it's
嗯。
responses received.
Some statistics.
未啊，開麥啊，唔該。開咗麥啊，不過。
As the market becomes larger and more complex.
The market faces a greater variety of risks.
Our market has experienced significant growth.
The joint consultation was launched in June last year.
The two regulators have to coordinate our efforts on different fronts to deal with these risks.
Following requests from the market, it was extended by two months and ended on eighteenth of November.
在 recent years， there has been rapid growth in the number of mainland private enterprises listing in Hong Kong.
總市場資本化額幾乎雙倍，從約13千億香港元到約25千億香港元。
在10年上，到去年年底，的士公司數量增加68%，從約1100增至近2000。
We will make a joint presentation with David today, so that I will do that in English, and then I will take on members' questions in Cantonese subsequently.
The market has evolved from one that primarily served local companies and businesses in the early 1990s, into a premium capital formation centre for the mainland and overseas companies.
And before we go into the summary of the responses, I will first outline the rationale and key objectives of the proposed enhancements. Then David will go over the key proposals, and then both of us will give a high-level overview of some of the.
我 pass it to David.
在terms of the preliminary summary of responses.
The objectives of the consultation are clear.
A significant number of the responses were without detailed explanation or comment.
therefore we think this is right time to review the current listing structure.
Under the proposals, the SEHK would remain the frontline regulator of listing matters.
然後，一個分離的清盤政策委員會，其職權是發起、引導和決定清盤政策。
We've received over 8,500 submissions. There's a wide spectrum of views expressed.
And this is at this stage, we are doing, and what we're presenting today is a high-level preliminary analysis.
This is still subject to in-depth study and discussion between the SFC and SEHK, and importantly, no conclusions have been reached at this stage.
The first is the listing regulatory committee, which will decide IPOs and post-IPO matters with suitability issues, or broader policy implications.
The enhancement should establish clearer accountability for decision making in listing regulation, as well as improve the transparency of the process.
Thank you. The key proposals there are really two essential elements to the proposal, which are really the creation of two new SCHK committees.
There has to be a right venue to promote strategic discussions on policy formation, and we have to exercise constant vigilance to address market developments.
The proposed enhancement should promote efficiency. They should enable the SFC and the exchange to coordinate and cooperate on listing policy formation and streamline the decision-making process for important listing decisions.
In terms of the categories of respondents, we've broken these down in order to give the the financial affairs panel just a very brief summary. We've broken it down into these category of respondents. I won't go through them in detail, but I will now just summarise very shortly what each of these groups has said.
terms of investment managers.
The vast majority of those who responded were in favour.
In terms of accounting firms, these are generally supportive.
和支持的設立LPC， to steer listing policy。
They support the objectives to improve the efficiency and effectiveness of listing and policy formation.
和The powers that it gives the SFC， and that the objectives can be achieved under the current arrangements.
They regard the proposals as timely and imperative amidst market quality concerns.
They also disagreed with the LRC's establishment and the LPC's appraisal of the listing division executives.
In terms of brokerage firms, corporate finance advisers and sponsors, the vast majority of these are against the proposal.
In terms of companies and related entities, as set out in our written submission, the vast majority of these are against the proposals.
they risk they talk about the risks of overregulation, slowing down of market development, and concentration in the powers of SFC.
They set out a variety of reasons for why that is the case, related primarily to the proposed structure being inconsistent with the existing three-tier regulatory system.
However, they do suggest in some responses that the stated objectives could be better achieved by a simpler solution, and a more streamlined approach could be adopted.
On the other hand, some some respondents in this category also talk about this being an improvement to the current regulatory regime, but also propose SFC representatives joining the listing committee.
again，there are other responses in this category，where which suggest that the proposals could improve the current regulatory regime，and where there is some support for establishment of the LPC，but with an expanded membership。
however they do also comment that under the proposals the power of the listing committee would be significantly reduced and detailed guidance on referral to the to the listing regulatory committee would be required and that the composition of the LPC and the LRC should be reviewed and expanded.
okay。
OK。
唔使再講。
just，yeah。
那 referrals to the LRC might lengthen the IPO vetting process.
那The SFC's power would be significantly increased under the proposals.
Okay, then I I will go fast forward to next steps.
嗱，喺嗰個文件之中咧，我哋咧就收到八千五百份嘅呢個回應嘅。
之前咧，誒，我想即係有個疑問，想問問政府，然後再畀大家討論，好唔好啊？
however, they do acknowledge that the existing regime has been in place for many years. The market has changed, and the current system has issues.
我哋最我哋係咧，我哋我哋揸緊時間咧，時間有限啊，所以簡單計算，因為我哋有呢個paper喺度。
They suggest regulators should focus on more robust enforcement actions to combat abusive practices, such as shell companies and backdoor listings.
在terms of law firms， the majority of these are against the proposals， on the basis that the proposals would not improve the quality of listed companies， or the efficiency of the listing process。
and suggest that instead of establishing new committees, SFC representatives could join the listing committee, or attend listing committee meetings involving suitability concerns or broader policy implications.
And for the category of legislators, for those who did not agree with the proposals, they have cited reasons, including the listing committee would be sidelined, the current checks and balances would be undermined.
So maybe we can and finally maybe chairman the the last slide that the SFC and SHK will carefully consider and analyse all submissions and prepare for the conclusions and decide the way forward. 好，唔使。OK，啊，不過即係喺議員嘅發言。
影響效率，同埋拖慢決策。
唔係，就可能咧就會適得其反。
啊，正如頭先我同埋啊David咧，係誒。
啊，都係主席，亦都多謝你來。我問咗我第一個問題。
誒，亦都有商界嘅人士咧，擔心喺新嘅建議底下咧，證監會。
唔會好似諮詢文件裏面咁講，令到整體上嘅程序咧有效率咗。
誒主席，誒上市公司嘅失當行為咧，即係要打擊嘅，大家都同意嘅，但係要用啱嘅方法。
喺上市委員會之上加兩個委員會，新嘅委員會咧，係會令到上市申請程序咧更加繁複。
啊！我首先重申啦，香港總商會咧係唔支持諮詢文件裏邊嘅建議，主要咧就因為睇唔到噉嘅做法會帶嚟咩嘅好處。
誒一人一票嘅方式，噉就係我哋係每一個分類咧，畀大家一個誒誒誒知道嘅方向同埋嘅原因，同埋啲誒贊成。O.K. 明白，第一位林建芳議員。
大部分都係反對嘅。我想問清楚咩叫反本色嘅回應？反本色係乜嘢嘅形式？同埋咧係有冇講明咧反對嘅理據？你睇下邊個答啊？唔該。
本來係打後衞嘅，嚇走咗上去打前鋒，令到上市審批嘅原則咧，就由披露為本變誒變做監管審批為本，即係。
贊成定反對係列落去，咁基本上咧係差唔多，除咗個名之外咧，係大部分嗰個內容係一樣嘅。咁所以就叫範本式。噉你哋點樣將呢呢啲噉嘅範本式嘅回應咧，點樣去即係去有個分析嘅結論咧？
噉啊，其中咧有八千份咧，就係誒個人個人嘅回應。咁政府就講呢啲係屬於範本式嘅回應。誒，我想問問咩叫範本式嘅回應啊？噉啊，同埋咧誒，佢哋入邊有冇指明反對嘅理由？因為八千份咧誒。
誒主席，或者我回答誒呢一個問題啦。咁喺誒數千份嘅回覆之中咧，誒有好大量嘅咧係差唔多係同一個格式嘅。咁通常咧，佢哋比較誒誒係就噉係兩三行，冇將詳細嘅誒原因誒。
我哋今日嘅工作咧，係誒告訴誒各位議員咧，就係我哋嗰個方法誒，就係將唔同嘅意見咧，係用唔同嘅分類。咁於是個界別咧，就係呢一啲泛本色，通常係個人嘅嘅意見。於是我哋將佢分類喺嗰方面，噉就唔係誒。
啊！
建議做唔做？
係告訴唔到大家嗰個時間嘅。
走回頭路，可能令到中小企咧更加難去集資。
Brian Ho回答係咪？好啊！誒多謝主席，誒多謝林議員嗰個提問。
唔識嘅方法嚟到去解決，咁但係當然我哋而家聽到聲音，知道有好多人誒持有唔同嘅意見。
對唔同持份者嘅影響，然後先至啊，再重新。
影響競爭力，甚至到會影響香港作為國際金融中心嘅聲譽，啊，衝擊自由市場嘅經濟。
咁另外，證監會有乜具體嘅措施咧，去規管同埋打擊公司上市後嘅違規行為咧？多謝主席。
噉啊！我有幾個問題嘅啊，其實當局咧幾時係會做好依個規管影響評估，去證明嚇你哋所講嗰啲係啱嘅嚇。
咁至於關於而家最後誒上市公司個質素同埋個規管嘅方面咧，我哋一方面好努力噉樣希望做好呢一個總結工作，誒優化而家制度；另一方面咧，我哋證監會繼續行使我哋現有嘅權力嘅。多謝。
香港總商會咧，亦都建議咗當局咧啊，做咗規管影響評估先，證明咗有改革嘅必要，同埋分析當中涉及嘅成本同埋效益。
咁另外咧就林議員提到個披露為本咧，咁香港其實咧誒從來都唔係全面嘅披露為本嘅。我哋本身咧誒上市規則裏面八點零四條咧，關於個適當性咧已經係存在咗誒非常之多年㗎啦。
誒，首先咧，關於誒林議員嘅意見咧，誒同埋誒佢嘅商會嘅意見咧，我哋非常之小心聆聽。我哋咧係誒會而家仲做緊分析嘅工作，未有一個誒總結嘅立場。咁所以時間方面咧，我哋會好努力噉樣去加快步伐，儘量係做翻。但係我哋喺呢一個階段咧。
咁至於林議員提到誒嗰個關於上市委員會誒，其實如果誒加多一重L.O.S上去咧，係一個誒呢一個加慢咗咧。當然我哋聽到呢一個意見，亦都好多人誒加咗啲意見。但係當時嗰個建議嗰個原意咧，就係基本上有一啲個案點解？
會係慢咧，就因為呢啲個案本身咧喺個規則嘅邊緣，佢本身咧就係比較接近咧，係有機會係誒受到監管機構嘅反對。咁而只不過當時嘅建議咧，就希望唔喺呢一度係清晰嘅議嘅個案裏邊，大部分嘅個案裏邊咧係加快咗，係用一個一紮。
係。
下一位係石禮謙，議員唔該。
張國軍議員、梁繼昌議員。
應該
措施。然而，我們必須做，within the legal framework of the SFO and the SCHK ordinance.
但係而家仲有五位語言要發言，我讀讀佢嘅名啊！誒，第一位係石禮謙語言，葉劉淑儀語言，郭榮鏗語言。
清楚咧，誒作為呢個配售嘅代理咧，佢嘅職責係要點樣工作？跟住咧，我哋有運用到我哋嗰個SMR嘅權力咧，係誒嚟到去啊處理咗呢個市場嘅問題嘅。
所咧係非常之關切市場嗰個質素問題。誒，我同阿David即係交易所誒有喺去年嘅十二月咧係作出一個聯合聲明咧，關於呢個公股誒，關於幾個誒。
Taking this into consideration as a committee member of the bill committee of the SFO, I think we did spend four years identifying the roles and duties of FSC.
而家最新嘅進展係點樣樣咧？呢個係第一個問題啦。咁如果而家諗住做嘅嘢，噉佢個效果良好，仲會唔會堅持一定要進行一個比較大動作嘅改革，定係話用一個小修小補形式都可以處理到而家面對嘅問題咧？唔該，主席。
好，第二位啊，陳振英議員啦，唔該。哦，多謝主席。誒，其實第一個問題啊，林建峯議員都問咗，因為呢個係一個非常具爭議性嘅一個諮詢啦。咁誒，當局喺吸收咗正反兩面嘅意見同埋理據之後咧，就應該要誒再睇下將來嗰個方向應該係點嘅。噉。
咁但係如果誒好似當局都未有一個確切嘅時間表咧，噉我想問另外兩個問題啦。第一個咧就係話未有新嘅方向，又或者未有任何嘅改革被審批之前咧，喺平衡市場發展啦、市場秩序同埋質素方面咧，證監會同港交所會先做啲乜嘢咧？誒？
誒何生唔該，好啊！誒多謝陳議員嘅提問。第一時間表，我諗我已經誒解誒向大家交代咗啦。咁至於而家誒關於我哋現在嗰個誒市場嘅問題咧，噉我就希望喺呢一度誒告訴大家咧，就係我哋同交易。
誒上市科作出嘅誒誒裁決，另外咧喺今年嘅一月咧，我同David亦都出咗一個聯合聲明啦，係關於創業板，我哋一方面咧就誒澄清咗根據呢一個上市規則裏邊乜嘢係一個公開市場嘅意思，同時亦都咧係澄清。
咁至於誒誒最後嘅問題咧，就係誒，因為我哋而家仲係好努力咁去做緊呢個總結咧，所以喺呢個階段，我只不過喺呢一度咧，同阿David咧，只可以誒同大家講講我哋收到同埋分析嘅意見，仲未喺一個時候咧，可以幫手誒講到誒個總結係會點樣。
主席，thank you, Chairman. First, I like to thank Mr. Ho for putting his case here today and making a decision that no decision is to be made regarding this consultation paper. I think that is very important. Second point is I like to make is that while we we really always
thirdly。
我 have yet to seen any.
If you have no time, you can answer me in writing. I prefer in writing.
to the merchant bankers, not to submit their views on this.
I don't know, not E or prior to E, that the.
That there is an absence of merchant bankers in their in their submission.
to that extent that they are not to be they are not to be there to participate in the market.
inclusion in there that you have just earlier presented under.
是是，the truth or not the truth? Please, at this moment, answer this question.
而家你做個presentation，就係列出所有給咗八千個回覆嘅人。
for amendments to the SFO and the stock exchange ordinance, you have taken into consider, you have taken into your own hands.
I was told that you can confirm, either true or not true, that there were efforts made by the SFC or the the other institutions.
rather than to supervise the market and let the regulators do the regulatory work. Now, what you're doing now in this in this consultation paper, instead of coming back to LECO.
I also like to hear views that you have not included in here. You have only briefly mentioned the opposition views, but you haven't really elaborate the views that oppose to this measures. Okay, three questions. Thank you.
changes to the structure of the two ordinances, you are acting against the spirit and letter of the two ordinances. That I like you to explain clearly, because Hong Kong, you have actually voiced this particular issues that you are acting ultravirous to that two whole.
整個issue在在做這樣的修訂，我們不希望看到諮詢來做法律的改變，如果有必要改變法律，回來到立法會。這是我們有義務去調查所有這些。第一個問題，第二個問題是。
冇。
誒下一位啊，葉劉淑儀議員。
呢個經常做咗冇一個間，主席唔好意思，真係好重要一個。有冇叫佢哋直接或間接叫佢哋唔好去？
去回應呢個諮詢文件咧，即係好多方面講嘢㗎嘛，係咪？即係好似你走去集差房噉，佢都叫你嚇。冇嘅，主席係。係。冇啊。
噉我自己亦都在場，我哋係解釋呢一個諮詢文件嘅內容，同埋大家聽取嘅意見。咁呢對亦都係喺諮詢嘅過程裏邊誒，經常做嘅一樣嘢嚟嘅。
誒多謝主席，或者我都跟進啊，石禮謙議員個問題啦。如果政監話佢冇去叫人冇畀意見，誒或者係要求人支持佢諮詢嘅。
監都有參與，但第日嘅LRC咧就你佔一半噉，即係你大曬，係嘛？呢個奪權嘅行為，而且咧，正如石禮謙議員講咗啦，法律上好有問題。
有關嘅諮詢咧係誒證監會同埋香港誒聯交所嘅一個共同嘅諮詢，咁政府咧係資識佢哋進行有關嘅諮詢，誒作為咧係提出一啲誒唔同嘅方案咧嚟諮詢市場嘅意見，政府喺呢件事情上邊咧係保持中立嘅，多謝。
O.K.，我諗咧，你可以用書面答覆啊石議員咧，好嘛？係啊，時間問題，我哋超時嘅啦。哦，好啊，主席去答咗，有冇去問嗰啲誒投資銀行？哦，噉你叫佢哋唔好去畀，因為睇唔到佢喺嗰個投資銀行，好奇怪點會喺度冇畀意見嘅咧？
啊！我哋證監會咧喺啊，我哋工作裏邊只會按照證券及期貨條例裏邊嘅職能咧，係做進行我哋工作嘅。我哋絕對冇誒畀任何壓力誒任何主席。即使佢哋未有電話畀到嗰啲merchant banks嗰啲誒管理人，或者係直接間接，我想。
要答呢個問題，點解我有我有有有懷疑同埋我有資料咧，係有噉嘅事情況，所以Mr. Ho你可以答咗我就得㗎啦嚇，冇有定係冇係我哋喺有同呢一個誒有有部分嘅投資銀行嘅誒，主要做保險人嘅工作啦，係有個會議會面。
財經副部局有冇啊？聽講話局長都走去幫證監拉票喎，有冇噉嘅事啊？局長財經副部局應該中立喎，其實應該監管證監會，唔好畀佢亂嚟。有冇咁做先？係咪怕咗證監會啊？女士唔該，係啊，多謝主席，多謝啊葉議員嘅呢一個提問。誒，我想重新咧。
啊！我好聽，高興聽到秘書長咁講。我真係希望係政府保持中立，因為我雖然唔係財經界人士啊，我都係投資者。我亦都係有聽到好多業界人士反對呢個誒建議嘅，即係已經證監誒港交所已經有個listing committee啦，無端端要加個。
L.R.C.L.P.C.加牀疊屋啊，睇唔到有噉嘅必要。雖然你把口就話增加個效率，其實奪權，即係你話曬事啊。乜嘢誒決定要嚟L.R.C.，乜嘢決定要L.P.C.啊？你話曬而家嘅listing committee廿幾人嘅。
港大嘅Asia Institute of International Financial Law已經寫咗廿八頁咧，話你係違反證監條例嘅，因為其實證監咧喺證監條例已經好大權，你可以批准，你可以取消，可以告人，可以罰款，可以檢控，已經好大權力㗎。如果你話有啲什
And as I explained in Cantonese earlier.
會小心聆聽，噉我亦都會誒知道係會留意、保持呢個誒開放嘅態度嘅。好。咁至於咧，即係上市委員會咧喺建議中仍然係保持誒大量嘅工作，所以亦都唔存在住我哋咧係攞去咗上市委員會本身嗰個職能嘅。
What you have proposed in the consultation paper. So, what what is the current thinking right now? Thank you, Mr. Hof. Thank you for the question. Because the concept of suitability embedded in Listing Rule 8.04 has been there for many many years. It is an old concept. It is not a new concept.
神仙股啊，老千股啊，呃咗啲投資者。你最近都有啊，最近咪有一單公司啊，朝頭早上市，下晝停牌嘅。你有權做啊嘛，做乜你要走去前台啫？如果你做監管機構走去前台管埋人上市，你窒礙市場嘅發展，我覺得係非常之唔正確。即係石。
議員話齋，如果你權力唔夠，你咪正正式式嚟立法會要求修改咯，係嘛？做乜要做呢啲噉嘅措施咧？嚇你答我啲問題啊！你你咩時候由listing committee決定？咩時候交畀LRC、LPC咧？你嘅LRC你應該係七個，應該六至七個人，你佔一半喎，你大曬喎。
啊，Mr. Brengle，啊，其實剛才咧，我已經誒多謝阿葉議員提問，誒已經解釋咗一次咧，就係因為本身咧，我哋喺呢一個諮詢嘅建議之中咧，係冇建議到對法例作出我哋兩個監管機構嘅權力嘅修改，咁所以咧中間。
咧係大家嘅權力咧係冇冇變嘅，所以唔長唔存在住一個誒奪權嘅嘅嘅誒目的喺一度嘅。咁所以咧就誒，但係我哋聽到誒，即係有唔同嘅聲音，包括啊類似啊議員所講嘅誒嘅嘅意見啦。噉我哋會。
啊！主席，其實阿何董事冇答到問題啊。我即係議員嘅問題，石議員嘅問題就係：如果你要多啲權力啊，你咪修改有關嘅條例咯，唔係話透透過一啲行政架構嘅改革咧。而家嘅問題咧，可以透過行政架構改革迴避咗修例而引。
Ultra virus嘅問題，呢個法律問題冇答到。若果聽到有人話咧，如果你夾硬實施，會司法復核你。我諗誒，而家好仲有好多議員要發言，我哋暫時延遲十五分鐘，大家有冇意見咧？啊，OK，噉啊，下一位郭榮亨議員。Thank you, Chairman.
As you know, many members of the legal profession have deep reservations about the proposal. I'm prepared to assume that the SFC and exchange are doing this in all their good intentions, and it is not as some have said that this is a power grab by the SFC. But there are, as you can appreciate, many genuine questions regarding the proposal.
特別是關於RRC的角色，當會將案件轉交RRC？什麼標準RRC會運作？以及在什麼基礎上RRC會做決定？這些都是實質問題，實踐者在企業金融領域有。
Regarding the proposals, so instead of creating a better system with more transparency and with better efficiency, the proposal thus creates the impression, at least, that it will lengthen the process for the listing application. It would create much more uncertainty for the applicants and the practitioners.
誒。
啊。
唔該，主席。
誒係一位係誒中國軍語員啦。
啊，點解會簡化咗呢一點？你要話到畀市場聽，話到畀個個嘅持份者聽，令到佢哋有一個即係説服力嘅答案。呢方面，我想聽一聽。唔該，主席嚇。
The legal points, there was clearly no intention to put something in place which would either be regarded as illegal or unlawful. Clearly, that is not the intention, and there was no intention to create any legislative change in relation to this process.
放幾個誒證監會嘅代表喺個上市委員會咧，我哋誒當時係相信誒呢一樣嘢係誒達唔到呢個效果，咁但係我哋會小心聆聽呢個意見嘅。咁但係根據呢個建議，其中咧有一樣嘢好重要咧，就係。
And it is wholly unclear how the RRC will operate. So I understand that you've heard the the various comments made by parties during the submissions. So what are you actually going to do about this RRC? Are you going to scrap it? Are you going to substantially change what?
The problem at the moment is that, because due filing acts are done by the SFC and the the exchange would sort of vet the listing applications. On the other hand, that actually is not a one-stop approach. Accordingly, the purpose is to reduce vast majority cases, so that would let them.
to be dealt with in a very more efficient manner, and accordingly focus on the difficult ones and then handle again using the one stop. Yes, so exactly, what what are the difficult ones and how are you going to select them? How are you going to tell the applicants your case is a difficult case which will be referred to the ERC? These issues you need to you.
Understood. I think we we hear all these comments very clearly. That's why we will take all these into consideration in making conclusion. Maybe I could just add to that. Obviously, I mean, in terms of as Brian has explained, suitability is already a concept which exists inside the listing rules. So the concept would just need to be, we understand the point.
Being made, but it's already a concept which is already embodied there. We would just need to kind of deal with it a bit more in a bit more detail. So we will take into account all the considerations that were made. I just like to go back to your very first point where you talked about that this was done with good intentions. It's clearly very important in terms of regulating this market.
That the SFC and the HKX work closely together in terms of regulating this market, and this was an attempt to put out a consultation, a proposal, and to get market feedback as to ways in which the SFC and the HKX could work closer together in terms of being more effective, in terms of regulation.
It's fair to say that we have a system which I think is operated very well, but it is fair to say it is not perfect, and it is clearly right to review that that process and to see where there are whether there are better ways to do it and to put that out to consultation. There is certainly no intention. I've noted the honourable member's discussions around.
我原則上咧係即係認同，即係證監會同埋即係聯交所，佢哋即係共同提出，即係你話佢改善嗰個上市同埋監管制度，或者嗰個嘅決策嗰個架構咧。誒呢個方向，我諗誒我係支持認同嘅。咁誒，正如但係喺你哋個進度報告所講咧，其實咧喺即係誒各個唔同持份者咧，有好多即係唔同。
嘅意見，甚至咧亦都有啲幾強烈反對嘅意見。咁誒，剛才你有都提過喺法律界裏邊咧，我特別指出咧，就係話佢哋講嘅就話，即係法律界個有個意見就話，建覺得個建議咧係唔能夠改善嗰上市公司嘅質素，又或者咧係提升嗰個上市程序嘅效率。究竟咧係咪能夠即係打擊個空殼公司啊、借殼上市呢啲違規行？
行為咧就非常之懷疑嘅嚇噉，所以咧就住誒誒呢一度咧，我就想問問咧，就係話嗱坦白講，如果你真係想做呢個改革嘅話咧，你一定咧就係話要有好強而有力嘅，亦都好有説服力嘅啊，去話畀持份者聽點解你要好似而家咁一個咁咁大嘅改動。
法律界佢提議就話：，喂，其實你唔需要咁即係一個噉啊徹底嘅改動啊。你會唔會可以考慮證監會？你喺個上而家嘅上市委員會裏邊，你反而增加你哋嗰個嘅委員嘅數目啊。喺個上市委員會裏邊去處理咧涉及你哋所講嘅合適性嘅問題，或者嗰啲所謂更廣泛政策影響嘅。
嘅問題喺呢個時間，你亦都可以及早介入嘅喎。咁亦都唔需需要一個好重大嘅一個嘅架構嘅改變。誒呢一方面，我希望即係聽聽究竟，即係你哋點樣去睇，即係法律界佢哋呢一種嘅嘅嘅疑問啊？點解唔可以用一啲簡單嘅方法？係咪即係佢哋提嘅方法？你覺得係解決唔到嘅問題，應該？
可好似你所建議噉係先至做到嘅咧。咁而你個建議又點樣符合？即係好似你喺改善措施嘅目標所提咧，你個建議點樣能夠話畀我哋聽係可以一個叫個程序簡化咗？誒又又或者咧，你所講嘅就住決策工作一個更清晰嘅問責問責安排，即係你加多咗兩個委員會，點解會更清晰？
誒，或者我先回一回答啊，中議員個提問。如果David想補充咧，就可以嘅。首先第一樣嘢咧，我哋嘅目標咧已經講得好清晰咧，係關於呢一個市場嘅質素，同埋我哋希望提升呢個透明度、問責性同埋呢個效率嘅。咁呢一方面咧，就噉。
啊。
啊，how？
係希望誒語言可以明白。
好，下一位係梁家章副主席。
proposals at the end of the day, which are both efficient.
my second question is in relation to legislators and political parties.
will will be one quite one-sided depending on on on what kind of business or professions they are in. There's my first question.
會有啲咩variation？喺呢啲類別，例如，以律師行或者書記行和贊助商為例。
Thank you, Chairman. I I do note that the accountancy firms and the investment managers are generally quite supportive of the reform proposal.
Do their view actually vary in accordance with the firm size, or whether they are local or international firms, or is it quite unique that their response?
The exchange are working closely together on a number of issues dealing with market quality, and they're doing that irrespective of what is going on in terms of this reform. But it's clearly important that we put out for consultation, given the changes in the market, to see whether the market felt that there should be changes to the way that this operates going forward.
現行咧嗰個，尤其是喺政策嘅制定，包括埋呢個市場嘅發展，包括埋好多誒保護投資者嘅政策呢一樣嘢咧，再繼續沿用於由交易所誒上市委員會提出，然後證監會咧係純粹係批或者唔批呢一個模式咧。
係未必能夠贏得上而家越趨複雜嗰個市場嗰個情況嘅，咁因此咧係有一個共同嘅地點咧，好讓啊所有決策嘅持份者咧係參與共同制定呢個政策嘅方向，包括埋市場發展咧，呢一個原意係非常之重要嘅。咁呢一樣嘢咧。
啊，主席，主席，請問。Okay. Okay.
And a structure which allows for efficiency and the way in which we can tackle market quality issues going forward. So we will listen to I think what everybody has said in terms of the responses and and come up with our conclusions accordingly. I think it's important for people to note that you know the the SFC and.
真係。
阿何生。
分析裏邊嘅，多謝主席。
唔係，我問佢政黨。
政治光譜。那係我第二個問題。多謝。
你講呢個會計嗰度？
好，最後一位係周浩鼎議員。
support the responses don't suggest that they are broken down and have different views depending on the size of those firms or the types of business that they undertake.
Regarding Mr. Lung's first question, I David may may supplement. I do not see any clear sort of a
regarding Mr. Lung's second question, actually there are seven legislators making comments, so it's individual legislators' comments.
Well, I do appreciate the authorities do take initiatives to revisit the current regulatory structure. I think nobody sitting here would disagree that we should enhance the standard or the qualities of the companies to be listed in Hong Kong.
And regarding your first question, as far sorry, Mr. Ho, how many political parties apart from legislators, individual? I haven't done the work. I mean, we have done the work. I haven't got the detail in hand. David, do you have that?
And that represent my own personal view as well. So I didn't want to go into detail. But your categorisation of responses is quite, you know, I would say unique amongst the different categories of respondents. I'm just puzzled.
how eager or how you know popular or or how many legislative political parties have actually participated in in the in the consultation or is it a very you know representative spectrum of political parties and legislatures of different
係而係違法嘅。
呢一樣嘢一定合法嘅，多謝主席。
好，最後我都想講一講嗰只業界嘅嘢。
就就呢個諮詢上次諮詢架構文件咧，我都同我哋行內接觸咗唔少嘅。
誒，首先咧就誒有好幾即係好多呢個意見係關於呢一個法律嘅問題啦。
啊，主席，因為咁多位議員啊提出過呢一個關於誒法律嘅意見咧，我諗我呢度要誒講多少少啦。
即係對呢個市場有咁大嘅反應，誒？你支唔支持呢個？想去諮詢文件咧，佢就反對喎。
咁而啊喺個諮詢文件，我哋已經講咗咧。我哋本身咧係冇對法律作出一個修訂嘅建議，因為喺個法律嘅職能咧，我哋係冇建議啊有改革。
噉我哋都仲喺度分析同埋考慮所有嘅意見嘅，噉我哋一定會喺準備就税誒發出呢個諮詢總結嘅時候咧，作出一個誒回應呢啲所有嘅法律嘅問題。
However, having heard many doubts raised by our fellow legal member, and as a member of the legal profession, I would simply be very much concerned about the legality of the new proposal, whether
一、一orial、written legal advice to address that concern before we make any sort of decision. Because I I don't think people sitting here would simply come to terms with any new proposal without reading a oral and written legal advice on that point.
主席，或者我諗就住呢一度咧，我都想誒澄清一下咧。我相信證監喺文件所提到話誒，關於立法會議員同埋政黨嘅回應咧，嗰度係指出一啲書面嘅回應。咁但係事實上咧，立法會咧喺呢一個誒場合之中，喺誒舊年嘅十一月九號就有一個嘅。
有頭質詢係阿葉劉淑儀議員提出，另外亦都喺二零一六年嘅十一月三十號咧。啊，主席，你都有提出過一個嘅動議辯論喺呢兩個場合裏邊，立法會議員有提出過嘅意見咧。誒，亦都係證監同埋誒交易所咧，都確認佢哋係會將佢誒參考喺佢哋一個嘅誒。
distinguishable features concerning the size or of the firms or or scale of type. Say for example, law firm. There are international law firms which support the proposal. There are also international law firms which are against. So I do not see a pattern in that connection. I would agree with Mr Ho in relation to that. I think it doesn't.
Your new proposal is against any law, as rightly pointed out by Regina. Whether this proposal is ultra virus or is against any particular provision of the SFC ordinance, so I think would you be able to provide us the our members?
噉我最想喺呢度強調咧，證監會嗰個職能同我哋嘅工作咧，係一定會按照我哋喺法律賦予畀我哋嘅權力，所以我哋係會採取最審慎嘅態度同埋標準，所以我哋一定唔會咧係誒喺總結嘅時候咧，會作出一啲誒總處嘅總結嘅建議咧。
咁所以咧喺呢個階段咧，我哋同埋聯交所咧，亦都喺度正在尋求啊我哋嘅法律意見。咁所以咧，到適當嘅時候咧，我哋會將所有意見同埋關於政策同埋法律嘅所有意見咧，係一並咁考慮，然後喺最後邊嘅總結嘅時候咧，係確保。
誒，我咧行內咧就好反對啊！嗰個市場咧充滿著老千股啊，操控市場啊，一日升幾倍啊，大上大落啊，同埋咧每次都合股向下炒啊！呢啲異欲，我哋小投資者咧，我哋咧就好呢個反。
對呢樣嘢，亦都我哋覺得正金喺呢方面咧做得唔夠嘅，應該加強力度去阻止。如果唔係，我哋仲話六千個市場咧就冇投資者有信心，所以最近我哋嘅師組嘅經紀咧好慘啊，冇生意啊，因為啲客就蝕曬啊。好啦，見你噉樣。
嗱，我睇我睇嗰個諮詢文件，我嘅意見。
文件用聯合諮詢兩個字咧，害死我哋業界。
嘅規則，但係咧，我哋又要即係點樣監管、加強監管呢啲流動？
我嘅意見就係咧改良嗰個上市架構諮詢文件，而咧取消咗個啊I.O.
咁呢個已經係充分嘅，正根有充分嘅去理解批核嗰個過程，所以咧就無需要再改變嘅。
以為咧，你兩個已經大家已經溝通好啦，個個嘅權責同埋義務大家都同意啊！你出嚟諮詢都唔夠兩三日咧，嗰個交易所嘅董事。
至於咧嗰個上市科技員工嘅花紅加薪升職呢啲咧，更加咧同證金冇關係嘅。我諗咧呢啲咧，我咧真係覺得咧，如果證金管咪真係權力過大㗎啦。
係普遍咧，即係錯誤嘅嚟到呢樣嘢，所以我就會覺得咧，即係政府各方面咧，要將呢個信息嘅呢個呢個呢個上市價格諮詢文件嘅內容正確嘅，即係發放畀市場嘅。
我問咧，你點解反對啊？既然咧，你嗰個誒反對嗰個市場嘅不法行為，佢話唔係喎。誒有人話畀佢聽咧，如果你支持如果上市結構諮詢文件咧，加大證金嘅權量，你就管死你哋。嗱，我覺得呢個信息喺市場咧。
即係話證呢個證監咧就提出嚟嗰個LRC啊同LPC啊，噉我覺得咧LRC咧呢個管制咧本身而家嗰個上市委員會已經有廿八人，呢廿八人咧亦都係證監同交易所聯合即係推薦嘅。
另外一個LPC咧，我覺得咧，即係嗰個而家嗰個金融科技嘅發展，我哋會產生好多啊！呢啲互聯網嘅公司，甚至類似阿里巴巴噉嘅嘢。咁所以我哋一定要定一個比較，即係涉及呢個市場發展。
就唔會好似咧，上一年咧，阿里巴巴上市咧呢個交易所係認同同意嘅，而證監咧就反對嘅。所以咧，如果呢個LPC咧，你LPC咧係成立嘅話，兩個嗰個單位咧一齊去。
對嗰個研究發展未來嗰個誒第三板咧，我覺得係適合嘅。如果你仲擔心啊兩個互相咧都猜測嘅話，你可以加多一兩個我哋業界嘅專業誒代表喺入邊。噉我覺得咧呢個ALPC係。
可以對未來嘅經濟發展係有幫助嘅，咁所以我覺得唔應該咧將整個嘅諮詢文件完全否決曬。我覺得市場改良咧係好事。有好多人話：喂，咁咧而家現時咧，你對呢個市場咧，你都
要出手啦，打擊嗰啲人啦。咁點解我哋唔講，即係唔理解成為咧，即係預防性嘅治療咧，咪更加好咯？個市場唔需要畀一班人咧，即係預約咗之後你先打擊，咁嗰啲散户就唔使受到呢個呢個無謂嘅損失啦。所以我。
C係啦，噉啊保留呢個LPC，咁呢個我覺得係對整嘅市場發展係雙方面都得益嘅。希望咧呢次交易所同證監會真係唔好誒口頭合，其實咧呢個內裏就不合。上一次嘅諮詢。
好。
噉。
嚟反對。
仲有冇？
多謝主席意見。
攞出嚟，畀我哋有一個指導。
高調嘅開記者招待會。
我都咁啦，冇得講。O K，好啦。
好啦，噉啊，多謝阿正金同埋呢個交易所嚇，多謝參加呢個會議，唔該，多謝。
咁咧證明咩啊？證明你哋兩個根本咧就唔係真心合作嘅。我希望呢次咧嗰個嗰個，你頭先講過咧，交易所同埋證監會會小心分析，同埋一個最後嘅呢個結果向我哋即係有一個誒交代，點樣去向前行？我覺得咧。
誒最最最好咧，儘早能夠有一個清晰嘅誒發展方向畀市場嚇，噉啊，亦都令到呢呢個呢個經濟發展可得以咧啊，即係嗰個儘快嘅進行。唔該，噉你睇睇咧會唔會再拖？會唔會有有有有好快有一個結局？